<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divisions cut in pieces by the svvord of the Lord: or, A discourse on a text of Scripture, of the unlawfulness of divisions in the Church of God, upon the highest pretences whatsoever. By John Rocket, minister of the Word at Hickling in Nottingham-shire.</title>
            <author>Rocket, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91916</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1764</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E593_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206903</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865997</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865997</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118256</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91916)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118256)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 91:E593[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divisions cut in pieces by the svvord of the Lord: or, A discourse on a text of Scripture, of the unlawfulness of divisions in the Church of God, upon the highest pretences whatsoever. By John Rocket, minister of the Word at Hickling in Nottingham-shire.</title>
                  <author>Rocket, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 81, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Maxey, in Thames Street, neer Benets Pauls-wharfe Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649. [i.e. 1650]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "ffeb. 21".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, III, 3 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118256:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DIVISIONS CUT IN PIECES BY. THE SWORD OF THE LORD: OR, A Diſcourſe on a <hi>Text</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> of the unlawfulneſs of DIVISIONS in the CHURCH of GOD, upon the higheſt pretences whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JOHN ROCKET, <hi>Miniſter of the Word at</hi> Hickling <hi>in</hi> Nottingham-ſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Ante admiſſum facinus improvidi, poſt facinus obſtinati; nec prius ſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, nec poſtmodum ſupplices: quando debuerant ſtare, jacuerunt; quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do jacere et proſternere ſe Deo debent, ſtare ſe opinantur. — Errorem pro veritate ſuſcipiunt.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cypr. de Lapſis. p.</hi> 224.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JAM. 5.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>— Know, that he which converteth the ſinner from the errour of his way, ſhall ſave a ſoul from death, and ſhall hide a multitude of ſins.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Maxey,</hi> in <hi>Thames</hi> Street, neer <hi>Benets Pauls</hi>-wharfe Church. 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118256:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118256:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE JOHN <hi>Earl of</hi> RUTLAND, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">AND TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFUL
<list>
                  <item>Eſqs and Knights for the <hi>Shire</hi> of NOTTINGHAM.
<list>
                        <item>JOH. HUTCHINSON</item>
                        <item>GERVAS PIGGOT</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>Eſqs and Burgeſſes for the <hi>Town</hi> of NOTTINGHAM.
<list>
                        <item>FRAN. PEIRPOINT</item>
                        <item>GIL. MILLINGTON</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable, and right Worſhipful:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a worthy ſaying of <hi>Aelius Trajanus,</hi> who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>Trajane</hi> in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Empire, <hi>Non mihi, ſed populo;</hi> ſignifying that which he was oft heard to ſay, <hi>Ita ſe Rem-publicam geſſurum, ut ſciret Rem populi eſſe, non ſuam:</hi> but it was
<pb facs="tcp:118256:3"/>a more noble and gracious Speech of a King in <hi>Judah</hi> to his Iudges, <hi>Non mihi, nec homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, ſed Deo:</hi> therefore God himſelf hath called you <hi>Gods;</hi> Gods towards us, but men towards God, yet Gods for God and us: they are not to look only downwards to us, expecting a duty that belongs to ſuch Gods; but look upwards and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the duty they owe to us by Gods appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that only makes Gods: And ſurely their Name tells them their buſineſs, and that they are not only concerned, but ought to have a ſpecial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to thoſe things, not only wherein their peace, but the glory of God is moſt involved. God in holy Writ much delights in two names, <hi>viz.</hi> to be a <hi>Iudge</hi> and a <hi>Father;</hi> when he comes towards the world in general, or towards his own Church chequered with good and bad men, you ſhall meet with him as a <hi>Iudge:</hi> but when he comes to his own, he calls them Children, and ſpeaks to them as a <hi>Father.</hi> The ſame hath he given unto his Preſidents in this world, the Magiſtrates; if they look into the Common-wealth to decide buſineſs, (though it be of Orphans and Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs) its in the Garments of a Iudge: but if to a Church, (ſuch as is, or ſhould be wholy his own)
<pb facs="tcp:118256:3"/>then as <hi>Fathers,</hi> as nurſing-Fathers. This I write to you, my Lord, and Gentlemen, not as your Inſtructer, but Remembrancer for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of this towards me (a ſmall member of the Church) as a Miniſter, I have found, and muſt acknowledge; which I deſire might extend unto the whole Church; which to be done by you, and others in the ſame Places and Callings, would much confer to the Happineſs and Peace of the Church of God (of which you are to be Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) and to your own private Peace, making your Callings to act towards ſuch high and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Ends, and for Him, who for himſelf, hath given you his Chaire of Iudgment; for which prayes</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant in the Lord Ieſus, JOHN ROCKET.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118256:4"/>
            <head>To the <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HAT thine and my Friend deſired for himſelf, is ſent to thee; and coming to thee, only deſires this of thee, To reade it with the ſame minde it was written, and for the ſame end; that ſo the Authors faults may be pardoned, the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders mended, and Gods name glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in the Unity of his Church and People; for which prayes</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> J. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118256:4"/>
            <head>Diviſions cut in pieces by the Sword of the Lord.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 3.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For whereas there is among you envying, and ſtrife, and diviſion, are you not carnal, and walk as men?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle having received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence from the houſe of <hi>Cloe,</hi> a family well known of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to be ſound in the Faith, zealous for the honour of God, and tender of the Churches welfare (elſe their credit had not ſo much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with him) and as well known to the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> to be of no leſſe note amongſt them, (elſe he had probably not been ſo particular in his Intelligencers to them) I ſay, having received In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118256:5"/>from ſuch good hands, of the ſtrange diſorders, and grievous diſtempers of that Church, writes this Epiſtle, as undertaking thoſe their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſed actings: and this he had not aſſayed but for <hi>Cloe's</hi> houſe. So that as its good for Chriſtians to watch over one another, ſo eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to keep a correſpondency of information with their chief watchman about the Spiritual eſtate of them, of whom he hath a peculiar charge, that ſo he might apt and prepare his Doctrines and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions for their conditions.</p>
            <p>Well, He hearing thus of the violent flames breaking out amongſt them, doth firſt of all la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to find out and diſcover unto them the prime occaſion of that fire; that, though but ſmall, but a ſpark tenderly nouriſhed amongſt them, yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes to hot and deſperate burnings. It aroſe firſt about their Miniſters, to whom they might owe much, and deem themſelves bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to acknowledge no leſſe, then to extol them according to their ſeveral apprehenſions of their eminent gifts, and powerful workings on them. But (admitting the Miniſters in ſubſtance to agree, and to Preach the ſame Goſpel) the people aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming this luxuriant liberty to ſet up one above another (whom God had placed with indifferency and equality of power) falls into dangerous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations, horrid diviſions, and unchriſtian pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Towards the Miniſters themſelves they ſo much admired; trampling under-foot whom they advanced, and overlooking their <hi>overſeers,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118256:5"/>
            <p n="2">2 Towards themſelves,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 In their unclean and filthy carriages, the hot movings of their unruly luſts one towards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as appears <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.</item>
               <item>2 In their Civil Commerce, by their bitter and ſelf-devouring Contentions in Law-ſuits, as <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. Such men as deſpiſe their Miniſtry, oft are delivered up to ſuch vile affections, walking croſſe to the Word as well as the Miniſtry.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="3">3 Towards their Profeſſion,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 In the wanton abuſe of all liberty, <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.</item>
               <item>2 In the profane celebrating of the moſt divine Ordinances, <hi>Chap.</hi> 10, 11.</item>
               <item>3 In entertaining that damnable Hereſie againſt the Reſurrection; as eaſily appeareth by <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. So ſtill the fire increaſes from the Church into their civil Stations, and out of them ſtill more and more violently conſuming the holy Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Truth it ſelf.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Apoſtle taking notice of this lamentable fire thus taking hold of all Relations, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming Miniſters, Families, Eſtates, Diſcipline, Worſhip, and Doctrine; begins at the Riſe, and finds the rent but ſmal: Yet ſees that the little The if is too much ſerviceable to put into the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and to open the doors for the reſt: He finds the head of theſe Troubles very ſmall, but the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it runs, the greater it encreaſes, inſomuch that all is over-flown. In this Epiſtle the Apoſtle la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to abate theſe: 1 By drawing down the ſwellings of their high thoughts one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118256:6"/>and leading the whole Church into a moſt neceſſary and uſeful ſubſerviency one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 2 By applying particular Remedies for aſſwaging of each particular Rupture, as you may ſee in their places. 3 By ſtopping the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and ſubſtracting the Fuel that firſt ſtirred up, and ſtill builds up this fire amongſt them. The oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of their firſt Schiſme ſeemed harmleſſe, nay good and commendable, <hi>viz.</hi> Each one ſetting up that Miniſter he thought of beſt: But Saint <hi>Paul</hi> takes that away,</p>
            <p n="1">1 By Apologizing for himſelf: and this ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neceſſary: for a great party in the Church ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared for him: <hi>Some for Paul.</hi> Wherein they might ſeem much to honour <hi>Paul,</hi> and that deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly, being a laborious and painful Miniſter, nay, and unchargable to any of them; much in ſufferings and dangerous tryals, yet continuing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, and ſtedfaſt in the Truth. Who could deny to follow this great Doctor, and to ſet up a Church for him? True, while they follow him to Chriſt, he could not but acknowledge them, and receive them into Communion, and encourage them therein; but when they make him a Sectary, a drawer of People to <hi>Paul,</hi> and not to Chriſt; or ſetting him up in oppoſition to any other godly and Orthodox Miniſters, to over-ſhadow their glory, who were his fellow-labourers, and fellow-helpers: then he rejects them, and ſhews to them what little cauſe they had ſo to admire him above others; and to follow him before others.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In reſpect of their beginnings: Though
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118256:6"/>he <hi>Preached</hi> to bring them unto Chriſt, yet he <hi>Baptized</hi> them not to ſettle them in a particular Church-way; and he thanks God for it that he baptized but few; as if they ſhould call after him, as if he brought them into a Church-Covenant, and promiſe to be his Followers, his Church, his Congregation, his Hearers, cauſing from them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Engagement againſt any other true Miniſters, or true Church ſociety. <hi>Chap. 1. v.</hi> 14, 15, 16. <hi>I thank God, that I baptized none of you, &amp;c.</hi> Not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he performed not the duty: but becauſe leaſt the performance of the duty ſhould have been an argument taken up by them to make him the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Patron, the Author of their Faction; which rather then to be to the diſturbance and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet of the Church, to the wounding of the Truth, he had rather not baptize them, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to produce ſuch ſad effects: and therefore he laying no Foundation or Inſtitution for a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Society, incorporating them into one Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; they could not juſtly, any Church, Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or Party, cry up <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, <hi>Pauls</hi> Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, <hi>Pauls</hi> People, more then, or not ſo much as any others.</p>
            <p n="2">2 From the manner of his Preaching; that it was far from entangling his Hearers, either by any Rhetorical and floſcular expreſſions, to catch the ears of ſome; or by ſmooth, ſweet, and inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating words,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 16.17</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſunt homines ſine malitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aut pravis intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus.</note> to beguile the ſimple and harmleſſe ſoul; or with Doctrines in an high Seraphical ſtrain, curious and ambiguous terms; here a piece of oyled Eloquence, there a ſubtile Diſtinction,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118256:7"/>anon a Phraſe wrapping the People into an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>viz.</hi> of words, and not of things: No, I ſought not thus to inveagle you unto my ſelf, to ſet me up in your hearts above another, that you might cry me up, and follow me rather then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: though I could do it, <hi>having the tongues, &amp;c.</hi> but thus and thus were my words, and thus and thus was my carriage, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4, 5. <hi>And I was with you in weakneſs, and in fear, and in much trembling. And my ſpeech, and my preaching was not with inticing words of mans wiſdome, but in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Spirit and of power: That your Faith ſhould not ſtand in the wiſdome of men, but in the power of God.</hi> That is, I made it my cheif bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe and deſign amongſt you, to declare and magnifie Chriſt, not my ſelf: for my ſpeech was plain, and my behaviour as modeſt: no boaſter, no deceiver: Say not therefore of me, That I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured in the name and way of Chriſt, to beget a Sect or Party to my ſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3 From the free unfolding and laying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf open to them, and all others view, and deſiring their judgement and eſteem, according to his own of himſelf. If he could rejoyce and glory of any thing, it was of his Office: but let them not dote on him in that reſpect: and therefore he ſeems thus to abuſe himſelf in an holy manner, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>Who then is</hi> Paul, <hi>and who is</hi> Apollo, <hi>but Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters by whom ye beleeved, even as the Lord gave to every man?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, And I pray you, who is <hi>Paul</hi> more then <hi>Apollos,</hi> that <hi>Apollos</hi> is left and cryed down before <hi>Paul?</hi> And what is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118256:7"/>
               <hi>Apollos</hi> more then <hi>Paul,</hi> that others cry him up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>Paul?</hi> What is he, or I, or any of us, that we ſhould be preferred by you, and divided by you? Are we not all Miniſters, and but Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial and Inſtrumental in our Series, and Places, and Seaſons, according to the gifts of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on us for your good? I beſeech you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, make not that difference amongſt us, which neither God hath made, nor we deſire.</p>
            <p>Hence we may obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1 That its an Apoſtolical way to oppoſe Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in the Church of God; to take away Diviſions, Separations, and with might and main to preſerve Unity; to hinder an exorbitant, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, and curious following and admiring of one Miniſter above another, though godly and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox: For here the Apoſtle denies it of himſelf,<note place="margin">Sub his nomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus pſeudo-apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolos taxat. <hi>Marlor. in 1 Cor. 3.5.</hi> Sic per proſopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poeiam alter perſonatus eſt.</note> and labours to take it from others: Yet whether he mean it of himſelf, and them nominated, (which I deſire to follow, being obvious and probable) none are taxed of the Miniſtry as making Church-Parties; but its ſolely charged on the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Its not good to deny a People to follow o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miniſters, where they ſenſibly profit in good; yet it is not ſafe for any to countenance them in it. 1 Leſt the perſons neglected have juſt occaſion of Emulation and Offence. 2 Leſt the perſon admired gather ground for Self-elevation. 3. Leſt the People grow further wanton, and fall into Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious and Scandalous Diſorders, as you ſee here they did. 4 Leſt evil claiming the ſame liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, even Servants, and others, make it ſecretly a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118256:8"/>way whereby the more eaſily, unſuſpectedly, and familiarly they may practice, and nouriſh their heady and corrupt Luſts: Let us therefore labour to follow this Rule, not to ſpeak, not to practice otherwiſe; and not like the <hi>Salamander,</hi> that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hiſſe but in fire; but the <hi>Dove,</hi> that cannot live but in his quiet coat.</p>
            <p n="2">2 We might obſerve, that the Apoſtle might accompliſh this his end, in his own reſpect, he humbles, he denies himſelf to caſt them off from himſelf: As when the People of <hi>Lyſtra</hi> would have deified <hi>Paul,</hi> he runs in to them, crying, <hi>Sirs, why do ye theſe things? We alſo are men of like paſsions with you, and preach unto you, that ye ſhould turn from theſe vanities unto the living God, which made heaven, and earth, and the ſea, and all things that are therein:</hi> Act. 14.15. Yet ſuch was the madneſſe, and ſimplicity of the People, that he had much adoe to hinder them. <hi>v.</hi> 18. And as he deſires to appear to them as a man, and ſo would not be <hi>Deified;</hi> ſo to theſe as a Miniſter, and would not be <hi>Chriſted.</hi> He a poor weak in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, that works not any thing by any Intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecal vertue of his own; and therefore throwing down himſelf, ſolely advanceth God in all their eyes. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>So then, neither is he that plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth any thing, neither he that watereth: but God that giveth the increaſe. Then</hi> hath the force of an inference; therefore ſince that neither I, nor any other can do any ſuch work (for which you do follow us, and make us ſingular) as from our ſelves, but from God; look not at us, but God:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118256:8"/>Is it the eloquent <hi>waterings</hi> of <hi>Apollos,</hi> or the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found <hi>plantings</hi> of <hi>Paul?</hi> No: we are but In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments; and Inſtruments, whether weak or ſtrong, are all one in the almighty Arm of God, which is made bare thorow us, and in you, that God may be all in all. And this hath been one ray of wiſdome ſhining in holy Writ from the Spirit of God, who Recording the Saints of God, doth own them in ſome things, that ſo we might love, honour and follow them: but in other things doth condemne them, that as Gods, we might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore them in nothing: And you ſhall not ſee the moſt accompliſht Portraicture of man without his blemiſh: <hi>Paul</hi> over his Excellency draws a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, that they might not look on him as a Chriſt: true, where they too much debaſed him, he boaſts of himſelf; yet where he is too much lifted up, he takes down himſelf, that he might not ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them and Chriſt; betwixt them and any Truth, or Miniſter. I have read what once a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſſe did towards her Lover, who being extrem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Melancholy at her frequent Denials, and ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of his tendered Services, and ſeeming to Deſpair, ſhe thought on no better a way to take off his Affection, and cure his dark Diſtempers then this: The next time the Lover came, and in his uſual Reſpects tendered himſelf to her; after ſome Diſcourſe, ſhe opened her Breaſts, whereof one was eaten to the bone with a loathſome Ulcer: which ſeen by the Lover, his fond Dotage was cured; and he ſatisfied with her Refuſals. So that <hi>Paul</hi> might take off their fond and unconſtant
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118256:9"/>Affections from him, they only looking on the beauty of his Doctrine, he ſhews the weakneſſe of his perſon; and inſufficiency of his workings of themſelves: It was <hi>Paul</hi> that ſpoke, but not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted; it was <hi>Paul</hi> that tendered, but could not give Chriſt: And ſure, if we all ſhould deal ſo, it would be much for our honour, and more for the Churches Unity.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Paul</hi> doth labour to cleer himſelf, and his practices, as not guilty of their Diviſions; he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Apoſtle, is loth to ſtand upon the File, (the Record and Hiſtory in the Church of God) that ever hereafter it ſhould be ſaid, That <hi>Paul</hi> had one Church, and <hi>Apollos</hi> another; that <hi>Paul</hi> had one Church that was not Chriſts; that <hi>Paul</hi> had a People better known by the name of <hi>Paulians,</hi> then <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and that he ſhould have a Church, that would not owne and receive the leaſt, and meaneſt Meſſenger of Chriſt Jeſus, as well as him. And though ſuch a pretended honour might ſeem to be thruſt on him, that it ſhould not be ſaid (when he was dead) That ever he would accept of it, and that he had left behind him a Sect called <hi>Pauls Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Pauls Church, Pauls Way,</hi> and not <hi>Chriſts,</hi> or any other Miniſters of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Paul</hi> having thus cleered himſelf from all ſuſpicion or ſhew of guilt that they or any others might lay on him, he proceedeth plainly and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to charge it home againſt the men, the firſt Authors hereof, and laies down the Cauſes and Grounds hereof, <hi>viz.</hi> That as the fire flames amongſt you, ſo it was kindled, and is nouriſhed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118256:9"/>amongſt you: It was not from <hi>Paul,</hi> or any faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſter, neither of their ſeeking or approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but you made a difference and Diviſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, with whom there was really none: and this you gave to them not of their minds, but your own, and that from a carnal mind, not a ſolid judgement, and right underſtanding. For <hi>ye are yet carnal: for, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to come a little more cleerly and diſtinctly unto the Text: The Apoſtle having in <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. laid down the ſecond part of his Plea, That it was no deſign of his, to draw a Party to himſelf, or to ſet himſelf up ſolely or chiefly amongſt them: and proving this from the manner of his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it being in ſimplicity, not in an affected, and ſelf-exalting ſtile; ſets forth likewiſe, That though the words were eaſie, yet the matter was deep, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the wiſdom of God, <hi>v.</hi> 6.7. and ſo deep, that the moſt eloquent in the world, being meer natural men, were not able to reach, <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9. and the reaſon is from the corrupt infirmity of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, inſomuch that he is utterly void of them, <hi>v.</hi> 14. But he that is a compleat ſpiritual man, thorowly regenerated, and truly enlightned, doth eaſily comprehend them, rightly receive, and fear ſuch things as he Preaches, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15, 16.</p>
            <p>Now the Apoſtle in an excellent Paragraphe paſſes from that general deciphering a meer natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral man, and a true ſpiritual man, to a particular Application of it to theſe <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and to them concerning this caſe in hand; <hi>And I, brethren, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118256:10"/>Wherin the Apoſtle divides the other two Parties, and joyns them in theſe <hi>Corinthians;</hi> yet I could not look on you as ſuch ſpiritual ones, nor yet as meer natural ones, but in a mixt eſtate of them both, or a middle betwixt them both; in the dawnings, or at leaſt not in the pure light of the Goſpel. And this he proveth from the Doctrine he was forced to frame and ſuite for them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their preſent capacities: He knew them and their abilities, though they knew not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: therefore he writeth to them, not as meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly natural, for its a ſpiritual Doctrine, and to them as in part acquainted with it: nor to perfect Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, for it was a plain and elementary Doctrine, called <hi>Milk, v.</hi> 2. which was good and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, though not hard, as ſtrong meat for grown and thriving Chriſtians. <hi>I have, &amp;c.</hi> that is, At my firſt entrance amongſt you, I then fed you thus, becauſe of your then weakneſſe, not my skill: and I muſt ſo feed you ſtill, for I ſtill find you little better, ſince I left you; ye are not yet able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive higher Doctrines; and no marvel, <hi>for ye are yet carnal,</hi> v. 3. And that they are yet thus car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, he further proveth in my Text from the preſent practice, a very plain and forcible Argument, <hi>For whereas, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mark the dependency of reaſon, and cleerneſſe of proof againſt them: he writeth now as before he taught them, a mean and humble Doctrine fit for their capacities; the reaſon is, becauſe he finds them for the moſt part ſuch as at firſt he met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, <hi>ſc. Carnal.</hi> They had made little or no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118256:10"/>(notwithſtanding their high and lofty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions) in the ſchool of Chriſt; he therefore keeps them ſtill in the ſame forms, and about the Principles of Chriſtianity: And that <hi>For:</hi> And that they are ſo <hi>Carnal, for:</hi> For <hi>ye are. For whereas there &amp;c.</hi> A cleer proof from the effects of the fleſh in them; for whereas at this very day ſuch envyings, ſtrifes, &amp; diviſions are amongſt you, is it not becauſe you are Carnal? for take me you when you were partly carnal, and minded not any thing of the things of God, then envyings and ſuch ſins were in the ſtrength in you: becauſe you practiſed according to your underſtanding: and ſince ſuch is your practice now, are not ſuch your minds? <hi>Whereas, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein obſerve theſe Three Parts:
<list>
                  <item>1 A Charge laid down againſt them. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 A demonſtration and proof hereof <hi>à po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriori,</hi> the fruits of a Carnal mind. <hi>Envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 The certainty of this proof made good in the Interrogation. <hi>For whereas, &amp;c. Are ye not, &amp;c.</hi> Such Interrogative Propoſitions being the leaſt dubitative.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But that we might fully handle theſe words, we ſhall reſolve the whole into theſe enſuing <hi>Queres,</hi> and reſolve them likewiſe with what cleerneſſe we can.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 To whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wrote this?</item>
               <item>2 What he laies to their Charge?</item>
               <item>3 How he proves his Charge?</item>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118256:11"/>
               <item>4 How it may be made good by plain De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratives, that his Proof makes good his Charge?</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt then of the Perſons to whom he writes, the <hi>Corinthians</hi> called <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 2. The <hi>Church of God:</hi> not that all <hi>Corinth</hi> was of, or in the Church: but that God out of thoſe Idolatrous <hi>Gentiles,</hi> had called by the word of his Miniſtry a People unto himſelf, to the profeſſion of his Name, acknowledgement of the Faith, and practice of his worſhip in peace, unity and order, and this he calls <hi>The Church of God;</hi> nor that this Church was contained in one particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation or Aſſembly, for it was a famous vaſt and populous City, wherein there had been many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and that had found a comfortable and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous acceſſe unto them; yet though many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, yet all one Church, and to hold one Faith, Worſhip, and Order, all being the Church of that only one God; and the Apoſtle afterwards doth give ſo large &amp; ſingular a teſtimony of them for their excellent gifts, that if we only had heard them and ſeen their faces, we ſhould have reported of them to have been perfect Saints indeed, and in no wiſe to be called carnal. And though a Church of God, <hi>called</hi> and <hi>ſanctified,</hi> to whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> makes an aſſurance of the <hi>faithfulneſs of God,</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their perfection and of their glorious preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation as blameleſſe once unto God, yet theſe have their envyings, their ſtrifes and diviſions.</p>
            <p>This I ſpeak, not that any Church ſhould hence incourage themſelves in their Schiſms and Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118256:11"/>that it may be a true Church, as dividing, becauſe a divided Church may be a true Church. No, this can follow no more, then becauſe Chriſt juſtifies ſinners, therefore we may be ſinners; and becauſe God owns a Church with ſpots, therefore its lawful to have thoſe ſpots; No, they are not beauty ſpots, but deforming ſpots: Diviſion is not ſign of a <hi>true Church,</hi> though ſometimes of <hi>Truth;</hi> But this I infer, that though <hi>love</hi> is an inſeparable affection of a brother, a Diſciple, a child of God, yet unity is no infallible ſign of a Church of Chriſt; for the deareſt brethren may differ, not as brethren, but as of different ages and capacities in Chriſt. If unity was (though <hi>Rome</hi> hath as little as <hi>England</hi> at this time to claim it) a ſpecificall and indiviſible character of a true Church,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.25, 26 Eph. 2.2.</note> then the Divels in hell may ſay they are a true Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe amongſt them is <hi>unity</hi> and <hi>ſubordination</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <p>Neither let any Church boaſt her ſelf of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute purity, perfection, and immixture; let them refine, purge, govern as ſeverely, watchfully, and ſpiritually as they can, yet there will be men, and children, and babes; ſpirituall, leſſe ſpirituall, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; nay, if it was poſſible to finde a Church without perſecution, troubles, envyings, and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion publikely, yet not to finde her without her ſeverall imperfections. But though Gods Church, Gods family, yet having <hi>yet</hi> corruption, being <hi>yet</hi> carnall, being <hi>yet</hi> men, and amongſt men, it may walk <hi>as men.</hi> Which calls in the charge laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> thus and thus honoured
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118256:12"/>and qualified. <hi>Are yee not carnall, and walk as men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Its ſet down interrogatively, but it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrs an indubitable,<note place="margin">Muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in loc.</note> and indiſputable Poſition. <hi>Are you not?</hi> that is, is it not clear and evident to all that have eyes to ſee and ears to hear theſe things of you, is it not a thing paſt queſtion to the judgement of all impartiall and godly men, that though it is long ſince I preached the Goſpel to you, and ſince you received it, yet you are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and walk like men? here be two Phraſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a little opening.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is meant by the word</hi> carnal?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Aliud eſt eſſe in carne, aliud eſt eſſe carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. <hi>Par. in Rom. 7. 2 Cor. 10.3.</hi> Illi in carne carnales, caro ſunt toti, &amp; tantùm: iſti non toti nec tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm ſed ex par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, quia ſunt in ſpiritu.</note> Its one thing to be <hi>in the fleſh,</hi> another thing to be <hi>carnall;</hi> every one before his converſion is in the fleſh wholy and all over, but afterwards he is fleſhly or carnall: Its one thing to <hi>walk in the fleſh,</hi> another thing to <hi>walk according to the fleſh:</hi> Every man living walks in the fleſh, but not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh;<note n="*" place="margin">qui ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſe vivit, ſecundum car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem vivere di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur. <hi>Aqu. 12. q. 72. a. 2. pri.</hi>
               </note> for this is to follow the principles, directions, wayes, and ends of a meer carnal and fleſhly heart, never truly and effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly changed in this world by the Spirit.<note place="margin">Carnales dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, quando totos nos volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus damus; ſpirituales quando ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſanctum praevium ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, <hi>i. e.</hi> cum ipſo ſapimus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruente, ipſo docemur autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. <hi>Hier. Com. in Gal. p. 933.</hi>
               </note> So the word <hi>carnal</hi> in a ſtrict ſence is put for one that is wholly in the fleſh, and ſavours nor at all any thing ſpiritually in the things of God, but is wholly addicted unto evill actions, proceeding from, and tending to the nouriſhment of ſinfull fleſh. But to clear this more fully we muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is <hi>Caro prima,</hi> the ſeed-plot of all ſin and root-corruption, called otherwiſe concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118256:12"/>this abides in the righteous after, as before converſion, but not in that freedome, ſtrength, and power, there being wrought in the ſoul a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous frame of Spirit, and general inclination to God, out of which flowes the particular acts of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, which are called diſtinctly ſuch and ſuch graces, ſuch and ſuch duties; and this is to be taken out of the old ſtock of <hi>Adam,</hi> of the fleſh, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall condition, and to be ingraffed into the new, Chriſt Jeſus, by whoſe vertue there runneth new ſap through the whole man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is <hi>Caro ſecunda,</hi> or <hi>ex prima orta;</hi> which is that manifeſt working of a man according to that generall leaven of ſourneſſe,<note place="margin">Non tamen in quibus nulla eſſet Spiritus Dei ſcintilla, ſed qui ſenſu carnis plus ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio adhuc a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundarent, ut pravaleret caro ſpiritui, &amp; lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men cjus quaſi opprimeret. <hi>Marl. in loc.</hi>
               </note> and root of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe in the ſoul; and this acteth as far as that ſpreadeth in their ſeverall ſeaſons, <hi>viz.</hi> over the whole man. Theſe are the ſtreams that boil up in the unregenerate, and bubble out of the regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, though penitent, beleeving, mortifying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and oft-times break out in a child of God (by reaſon of a ſpirituall <hi>Antiperiſtaſis</hi>) more ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and violently then in a wicked man; and ſome particular ſinful actions in themſelves and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances may truly appear more grievous then in others; ſo that theſe are carnall (as the <hi>Corinthians</hi> here) in this reſpect, and that for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe of that <hi>ignorance</hi> which is in them,<note place="margin">Carnales dicum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>1.</hi> Ob co rum ignoranti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</note> whereby in part they diſcern ſpiritual things, and ſo in part are carnall, and therefore the Apoſtle joyneth theſe two, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe of that inward oppoſition and <hi>ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in him betwixt the Spirit</hi> and the fleſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Ob internam reluctantiam.</note> that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118256:13"/>though the whole man voice it not for ſin, yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is he without his ſidings and votings with ſin.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Ob externam praevaricatto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note>3. Becauſe of ſome <hi>deeds of the fleſh</hi> (of which they have, and do afterwards repent) which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times proceed from them.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">Ob peccandi poſſibilitatem.</note>4. Becauſe of the common condition of all <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the fleſh,</hi> being obnoxious and lyable to the infirmities of the fleſh.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin">Ob peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum imitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; carnis in eis quanda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ill a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lonem.</note>5. Becauſe of thoſe ſecret <hi>movings of the heart to all ſin</hi> in particular, in ſome leſſer degrees; though he abhorreth and proceedeth not to murther, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet there are ſome daily paſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though he proceed not to Fornication, Adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet there may be a wanton eye, a vain word, a looſe thought, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though even for theſe and leſſe, if leſſe may be, he is offended with himſelf, and mourns before God: yet in a degree here are the actings of the fleſh in a child of God, and ſo they are trully carnall, and accordingly are more or leſſe carnall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Concerning the other Phraſe to walk <hi>as men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word here <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is not as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the firſt verſe, and the difference is much;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for the firſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth only a kinde of ſimilitude, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a kinde of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity; and yet it is one thing to walke accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>to the fleſh,</hi> and another to walk according <hi>to man.</hi> For the firſt of theſe (as before you had it) by way of excellency doth ſet forth to us a man in his unregenerate condition, following meerly the dictates of corrupt reaſon, and all his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118256:13"/>actions tending to himſelf. But <hi>ſecundum hominem ambulare,</hi> is,</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Secundum praecepta hominum;</hi> when though we walk the right way, yet being led by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and examples of men, its but a carnal acting in a ſpiritual way: and hence is that expro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13. wherein he reproves not the matter of the fear, the worſhip, ſervice, &amp;c. but the ground and cauſe of it being humane, taught of man; notwithſtanding the Lord had ſeveral wayes inſtructed them by his Prophets, and his Judgements; yet by theſe they would not learn as from the Lord, but only by the civil Sanctions of men: and ſo here in my Text it hath relation; even thus you walk as men, or according to men,<note place="margin">Secundù ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare, <hi>i. e.</hi> huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis duci affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. <hi>Muſc.</hi> Ambulare ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundùm homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem eſt non tantum hominus carnalis opera facere, aut tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum vivere ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundùm car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ſed etiam ſequica, quibus homo carnalis nititur: quales ſunt res, huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ſapientia, ratio, natura, &amp;c. hinc patet &amp;c. de tota<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis natura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praedicari. <hi>Marlor. in loc.</hi>
               </note> to <hi>Paul, Apollos;</hi> what theſe men ſay, but not as they Preach the Word of the living God, and Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Secundum;</hi> that is, <hi>juxta,</hi> or <hi>inſtar.</hi> You walk even in this reſpect as other men that beleive not, that profeſſe not the Goſpel, but are but <hi>meer men.</hi> Hence is that prohibition of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. Herein there is in theſe Chriſtians a great conformity to the reſt of wicked men in the World. Therefore as in the firſt <hi>verſe</hi> he doth not call them abſolutely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that, as in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going <hi>Chapter,</hi> taſted nothing of the things of God; but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that much relliſhed the things of nature; for they were ſanctified and regenerated in part, but had yet the ſtraines of the old man, and did in many things, even in theſe, much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble him. For in theſe their preſent actions,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118256:14"/>they were more like what they were before they believed, and what their natural Country-men, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters, are, then Converts, and Spiritual. For if you profeſſing to be ſpiritual, do but compare your ſelves with ſpiritual men, or the ſpiritual let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, you much fall ſhort; but if with carnal men, behold, <hi>Manifeſta ſunt opera carnis,</hi> you ſhall find your deeds to be even as theirs, and your walkings to be according to ſuch men; and therefore you are but carnal, but men. And this brings me to the proof of this ſo ſaid, how and in what parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular actions he proves them ſuch; <hi>Whereas ye are, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 The proof of the Apoſtles Charge in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, which is from their actions, the ſad effects of a carnal minde: Thus,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They that performe the works of the fleſh, are fleſhly; but ye</hi> Corinthians <hi>performe the works of the fleſh:</hi> Ergo.</p>
            <p>The Major is cleer; mans judgement can reach no farther then the appearance: nay, its not only the judgement of right reaſon, but of the Spirit it ſelf, that ſentences a man according to his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and common actions. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.11, 12.</p>
            <p>The Minor is cleer, that they do act the works of the fleſh; for, do they not know the deeds of the Fleſh, and the fruits of the Spirit? The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle firſt ſets down carnal deeds, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20. having before diſcovered the fountain, there being two heads in every gracious man, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Spirit;</hi> and theſe two ſtrive firſt for paſſage: now if ſuch ſtreams as theſe flow from us, they proceed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118256:14"/>from the fleſh. And theſe very Three things are enumerated in that Catologue, only tranſlocated.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Strife,</hi> or <hi>Contentions, Envyings,</hi> or emulations, diviſions, or Sects. Thus he ſets the works of the fleſh, and ſpirit contradiſtinct, and oppoſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ſo does <hi>James, Chap.</hi> 3.14, 15. <hi>But if ye have bitter envying and ſtrife in your hearts, glory not, and lie not againſt the Truth. This wiſdome deſcendeth not from above, but is earthly, ſenſual, deviliſh;</hi> Earthly and heavenly wiſdome;<note place="margin">where we find theſe two <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the ſame order as in my Text.</note> the nature of earthly wiſdome (wiſdome falſely called) was to envie, out-ſtrive, weary one another with diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſuch was humane wit and wiſdome; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle he follows theſe witty actions home, and diſcovers the riſe, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.1. Well, its plain then that theſe envyigns, ſtrifes, and contentions, and diviſions are properly the workings of a carnal and unſanctified ſpirit. But to the words; <hi>Whereas there is Envying, Strife, Diviſion:</hi> Mark their ſeries and graduation: firſt <hi>Envie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctore, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in linguâ, et <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peribus.</note> that begins to kindle firſt in the <hi>heart,</hi> and burn, and burns till it ſet fire on the <hi>tongue,</hi> and then breaks out <hi>Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> and from <hi>words</hi> it falls to <hi>deeds;</hi> that from jarrings and ſcoldings, they quite fall aſunder and part; whence are your <hi>Diviſions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then a word of your <hi>Envyings.</hi> The word in the Original comes of a word that ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies <hi>To boyle with heat;</hi> and this <hi>envying</hi> is a <hi>boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. hence thoſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithites, <hi>pallidus irâ</hi> &amp; Heſ. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> a vehement, hot, diſcontented, and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome motion of the affections againſt a perſon, or cauſe not beloved, but an enemy to ſomething that the party ſo affected loves. And as men that deal
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118256:15"/>much in the fire waxe pale and wan;<note place="margin">Such is the Deſcription of anger with the Poets. See it elegantly in our Engliſh <hi>Virgil.</hi> This is <hi>zelus invidiae, non zelus conjuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis;</hi> or <hi>ipſa in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidia,</hi> as right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſlated.</note> ſo doth this fiery affection dry up the good qualities of the Soul, contracts and draws into himſelf all the good deſires, nay the very good looks he owes to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; as it takes away the colour of the face, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like death, and by his looks promiſing no leſſe in ſome degree or other to the party diſaffected, ſo that with the colour of the face departs the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the mind. This is the nature of this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, this emulation, this envying betwixt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and here is the difference betwixt anger and envying (though confounded in the tranſlation) that <hi>Envie</hi> is a <hi>continued Anger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quo quidem malo neſcio quis noſtrum caret, &amp;c. et poſtea— neſcio quis poſſit regnum Dei poſſidere, cum is qui iraſcitur ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paretur a regno. — Inter Ira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundiam et i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram hoc inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, iracundus ſemper iraſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, iratus pro tempore conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur. <hi>Hier. Comment. in Gal. p. 937. vide</hi> Weems, <hi>the portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of man.</hi> vol. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>188.</hi>
               </note> or a real, fervent, and hearty deſire of an other mans evil, ariſing out of anger, to which all are ſubject, <hi>viz. Anger:</hi> and God owns it in himſelf, and ſo it is good accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to its object and carriage, as zeal is likewiſe: only as it is ſinful, <hi>hatred</hi> hath an <hi>injury</hi> for its ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; but <hi>envie</hi> hath the <hi>proſperity</hi> and happineſſe of others for its object: As <hi>David</hi> conquering of <hi>Goliah</hi> made <hi>Saul</hi> envy him; and the Prodigals good and free entertainment provoked his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And therefore farre worſe then anger or hatred.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This cannot continue long in the heart undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, being in a multitude, one Church bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with envie in Spirit againſt another; but as heat cauſing aire in any concave bodies, produceth diſquiet motions till it findeth its paſſage; and as hot <hi>boyling</hi> liquors will ariſe out of the belly over the lips of the Pot; ſo this will out of the mind and perplexed thoughts, and break through the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118256:15"/>mouth and tongue into railings, ſtrifes, invectives, contentious diſputes, &amp;c. which is called this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, promiſcuouſly uſed and tranſlated: When men out of an affectation of glory, and deſirous of victory, encounter with men profeſſing and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent in the Truth, begin <hi>unneceſſary ſtrifes,</hi> and endleſſe diſputes about words, things of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency, caſes of ſuſpition, and moſt about things (when reſolved) not much making for edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; but in the mean while to continued per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations: from the practice of which, and the ſociety of ſuch diſpoſitioned men, the Apoſtle fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently warns and dehorts <hi>Timothy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Theſe cannot continue long; but from <hi>words</hi> to <hi>blows;</hi> the Apoſtle therefore adds to this, <hi>Wars, Jam.</hi> 4.1. or at the leaſt to <hi>Diviſions:</hi> For if they envy, and then jarre and quarrel, and will not hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and carefully take up (as ſeldom men of ſuch ſpirits do) theſe cannot continue long together in one Church and Congregation, but muſt divide, and that in oppoſition and deſpight one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And here follows after envying and ſtrife theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Diviſions.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 3.3.</note> We ſee one houſe could not hold <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> becauſe of <hi>Iſhmaels</hi> proud contentions, and fond mockings; which is more ſubject to the baſe-born, then the free and true born of the Lord. We ſee that <hi>Lot</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> could not dwell neer together for this, but divided far aſunder; though <hi>Lot</hi> fared never the better, who was the <hi>cauſe</hi> of the diviſion, and could not ſtoop to <hi>Abraham,</hi> his betters. And ſo it is in the Church of God; for after ſtrifes and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118256:16"/>envying, then comes Sideings, Parties, Sects, Factions, ſeveral Churches according to the things they envie one another, and ſtrive with one another about. And this comprehends Hereſie and Schiſme, which ariſes from Envie, Pride and Strife, and conſummates the diviſions. Envie is the firſt riſe that divides the tongues, and makes one ſay this, and another that, ſtriving for maſtery, and glory above another; and hence it is, That one will not ſee as an other, will not ſpeak as an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, will not walk as another; but will contend againſt them to vex and diſhonour them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: cum ſcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet ſibi unus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſque eligat diſciplinam (po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius doctrinam) quam putat eſſe meliorem: qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque igitur aliter ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram intelligit, quàm ſenſus ſpiritus ſancti flagitat, quo conſcripta eſt, licet de Eccleſia non receſſerit, tamen haereticus appellari poteſt. &amp;c. <hi>Hier. in Gal. p. 936.</hi>
               </note> will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide from them to ecclipſe and leſſen their glory. Hence comes many an <hi>Heretick;</hi> which is not diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Latin word <hi>Haeres,</hi> but from the <hi>Greek</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is a taking unto our ſelves a Point differing from the Truth and Church of God in a Fundamental: and ſo a man walking this way, may be an Heretique whether he divide from a Church or no; only he will divide, becauſe a true Church cannot ſuffer him to continue with them: and others will go further, (I will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine whether with more Judgement, or leſſe Charity) adjudging them to be Heretiques, who will obſtinately, and perverſly againſt all means, conſcionably and holily uſed by the Church to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime them, continue in an Errour to the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance and vexation of the Church,<note place="margin">See the pious Exhortation of the <hi>London</hi> Divines at their late ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, p. 131. 132</note> though not in Fundamentals. The reaſon is, Becauſe <hi>Perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy, Obſtinacy,</hi> and <hi>Impudence</hi> is of the <hi>forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of Hereſie.</p>
            <p>And as for Schiſme, being no Latin word, it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118256:16"/>comes not <hi>a ſcindendo</hi> (though of ſome affinity as in the former) but of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that ſignifies <hi>To rent,</hi> or <hi>divide;</hi> and ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is in a proper ſenſe called <hi>A rent, Matth.</hi> 9.16. And this hath reference to the Government of a Church, yet not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the Excommunicate perſon who is a Schiſmatique, but its <hi>paſsively,</hi> and he is deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly made ſo being cut off from Church Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; and not of another, but of no Church: but this hath reſpect to ſuch as are Schiſmatiques <hi>actively,</hi> cutting themſelves off from a Church, and ſetting up another Church-way in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to their own private judgement, or their groundleſſe ſpiritual fancies; leaving their former Aſſemblies, and in contempt, deſpite, and oppoſition to them, ſets up others: Such an one is a moſt compleat and abſolute Schiſmatique, who out of a ſingular conceit, and end of their own, leaves the general way of the Church, and walks in one of their own: The Engliſh of ſuch a man is a <hi>Sectary,</hi> which comes a <hi>Secundo,</hi> who divides himſelf from a Church ſound in the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of Religion, and endeavouring in Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come to the moſt plain and exact Scriptural rules. Theſe are your <hi>Dichotomiſts</hi> that divide and ſub-divide themſelves ſo long,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>of</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> dupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer, <hi>and</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeditio. ſtatio, <hi>hence</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, idem ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant.</note> that you ſhall find no Church, I am ſure no univerſal Church; and their particular Churches will be as many as there be perſons almoſt, in time: And hence come your <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>diviſions;</hi> which are either from perſons once of one mind and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but now parting themſelves, plot and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118256:17"/>for, and walk in ſeveral wayes: Or elſe its a ſpiritual <hi>mutinying,</hi> and <hi>ſedition</hi> in the Church of God, where one Party cryes <hi>up</hi> this, another that; and at laſt unſatisfied, go their ſeveral way like <hi>Iſrael</hi> under <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> 2 Chron. 10.16, <hi>Every man to your Tents, O Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> and every man to the way that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears beſt unto him; like an Army either rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thorow the ſtrength of an Enemy, or moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring away for want of good Government and exerciſe.</p>
            <p>The ſenſe is this; O ye <hi>Corinthians,</hi> among you are envying, ſtrifes, and diviſions of theſe natures, and degrees; ſome of you ſetting up a Church in the name of <hi>Paul;</hi> another Party a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Church in the name of <hi>Apollos;</hi> a third in the name of <hi>Cephas;</hi> and theſe you do in oppoſition one to another; violently maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one to be better, and more excellent then another: and yet for all this, you will be the <hi>ſpiritual ones.</hi> What? Are theſe the fruits of the Spirit and a ſanctified heare? Does it bring forth ſuch Bryers and Thornes? Does it work no better a change on the vile natures of man, but that ſtill you ſhould have the ſpirit, and diſcover the cruelty of a Wolf, the gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe of Doggs, the deadly poyſon of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and the cruelty of all Beaſts? What is't a ſpirit of Diviſion, Strife, and Envyings? No; ſuch comes not from the Spirit, but quenches and ejects it; ſuch ſhews not the heart of a <hi>ſpiritual man,</hi> a <hi>Dove,</hi> a <hi>Sheep:</hi> but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118256:17"/>the contrary. And an happy and acceptable thing it is for that Church,<note place="margin">Haec eſt in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia noſcenda ſimplicitas, haec charitas obti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenda, ut co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbas dilectio fraternitatis imitetur, ut manſuetudo et lenitas agnis et ovibus coaeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Quid facit in pectore Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiano luporum feritas? Et canum rabies, et venenum letale ſerpentum? Et cruenta ſaevitia beſtiarum? gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulandum eſt, cum tales de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia ſeparan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ne colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas, ne oves ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vâ ſuâ vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natâ contagione praelentur. <hi>Cypr. de Unit. Eccleſ.</hi> p. <hi>233.</hi>
               </note> where ſuch are divided from them, that the harmeleſſe <hi>Dove,</hi> and quiet <hi>Sheep</hi> be not ſpoiled and poyſoned with the violence or ſubtilty of their diviſions: And doth not the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit rather take down the ſwellings of the Proud, meeken the ſpirits of the ſtout-hearted, unite the hearts of enemies, inſinuate its oyls of humility and ſelf-denial into the juſtified; and brings all hearts of what nation, or condition ſoever (if a <hi>Barbarian, Scythian, Armenian, &amp;c.</hi>) into one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement? Sure it is then, that you deceive and miſtake your ſelves: in theſe reſpects you diſcover but a carnal, unſanctified, unregenerated, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed heart from your firſt condition. And this brings on the laſt <hi>Quere,</hi> How by good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration may this be made good, that envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, &amp;c. are the proper fruits of the Fleſh, and not the Spirit?</p>
            <p n="4">4 To make this good by cleer demonſtrations, That Envyings, Strifes, and Diviſions (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their higheſt pretences) for <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos,</hi> or <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, proceed from the fleſh, and in that reſpect diſcover a meer carnal, and not a ſpiritual mind.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The Firſt is drawn from the firſt breakings out of corrupt nature from man after his fall, wherein it will appear, That our dividing from God in our affections, is the cauſe of our diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons one from another.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Conſider this Diviſion as a <hi>divine revenge</hi> on backſliding man; and you ſhall ſee it a meer fruit of ſin.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:118256:18"/>
            <p n="1">1 There is a diviſion in the <hi>nature of man.</hi> When God made man, he ſo equally tempered the quarrelſome elements in mans body, that they (who of themſelves would deſtroy one another, and thereby the whole frame) ſerve one another willingly to the preſervation of man: <hi>but in the day that thou eateſt the forbidden fruit, thou ſhalt die;</hi> that is, become <hi>mortal.</hi> Soul and Body that made up one before, and was to remain one, muſt now be divided; and therefore there muſt be oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions amongſt the contentious humours of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; this or that ſtriving for predominanty: And being diſtempered and diſeaſed, becomes unfit for the Soul, deſtroyes the Spirit, and baniſheth the Soul to him that firſt joyned them to the Body.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A Diviſion <hi>with the creatures.</hi> They were all made to ſerve man, and man could not in his <hi>innocency</hi> more freely and cheerfully have ſerved his maker, then being innocent they ſhould have unanimouſly and promptly have ſerved him: That as he gave them names, ſo he ſhould by theſe names, like the good <hi>Centurion,</hi> ſet over the <hi>hoſt</hi> of God, call and ſend them at his pleaſure. But now becauſe man hath loſt his <hi>integrity,</hi> he loſeth his <hi>dominion;</hi> and as they War againſt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo rebell againſt their Lord and Maſter, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to be ſubject to him: And inſtead of living one with another, one lives upon another: And as ſome obſerve, The worſt of creatures hath ſome good in it to preſerve and help man, ſo the beſt of creatures hath ſomething in it to deſtroy man.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118256:18"/>
            <p n="3">3 A diviſion <hi>with man;</hi> betwixt the good ſeed and the bad, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Ego ponam, non ut vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, ſed ut poenam.</hi> That as there is an inveterate and irreconcileable hatred betwixt the natural Serpent and mankinde; ſo betwixt the ſpiritual ſeed of the Serpent, and of the Woman: and not only the wicked and the godly are thus divided, but the godly themſelves, even amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo far as natural and carnal.</p>
            <p n="4">4 A general diviſion <hi>amongſt all men:</hi> not only in their hearts, but in their tongues and wayes too; and all ariſing from <hi>envy.</hi> Before Satans envying the happineſſe of God, and deſiring to be like unto him, there was no diviſion; but then he, thruſt out of the preſence of God, ſeeing that not feaſiable to become as happy as God, being now become miſerable, is loth that any ſhould be more happy then himſelf; he therefore envying mans felicity, ſets him on a point of emulation, ſtriving, and aſpiring to be like God, and ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides them. Then his poſterity, either proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſdaining the judgements of God, or enviouſly attempting heaven, builds a Tower; and then God curſes their <hi>language</hi> with <hi>diviſion,</hi> that they have the curſed gifts of ſpeaking ſeveral languages, or elſe that one language ſo variouſly dialected, that they could not underſtand one another. And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they could not live, rule, plant, build toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but every one according to his tongue and his family betakes himſelf into ſeveral parts, and there hath his ſeveral God; and when grown up into Countries and Nations, they War one againſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118256:19"/>another; and thoſe that could not live together, cannot live one by another. And we ſee theſe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments continuing and encreaſing with the ſins of mem amongſt the Church of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Conſider this diviſion as naturally <hi>ariſing ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully from ſin:</hi> What God inflicts as a puniſhment, man practiſes as a ſin; and in both theſe reſpects it firſt breaks out in <hi>Adams</hi> own family (ſeeing the truth of the Curſe performed before his own eyes, and on the fruit of his own loins) as a moſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine ſtream of a corrupt heart. The Apoſtle joyns theſe two together, Envying, Murder, &amp;c. <hi>Murder</hi> is the height of <hi>diviſion,</hi> when not only they cannot abide to be together, but cannot abide to be at all: like fire and water, either part them, or they muſt conſume one or other, or both die to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Man cannot love, nor unite his affection to any thing that is good, not to God himſelf, or his Truth; becauſe man is become ſo much bad, that there is nothing that is good but its an enemy to him, and therefore he ſeeks to his power to deſtroy it: As we reade of <hi>Cain,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.12. <hi>And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſlew he him? becauſe his own works were evil, and his brothers righteous.</hi> Satan is called the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, and the envious to be of him. Envie, and ſo Satan may be very well called by the Serpent Baſilisk, who is termed <hi>Rex invidorum;</hi> becauſe he tranſmits death from his eyes, ſeeing others well, conveyes his poyſon immediately to hurt them. Natural wiſdome is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.14. Satan is ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. and his employment is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in ſleeping time,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118256:19"/>in the very hour of our negligence, &amp;c. he ſowes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>weeds,</hi> not only making evil men amongſt others in the Church of Chriſt heretiques, &amp;c. but even in the hearts of Gods people; when they are careleſſe and watchleſſe, he caſts in tares, envious motions, dividing thoughts, proud, ambitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns into the heart, &amp;c. this is his main buſineſſe he goes about. But none of his temptations could ſet fire on us, but that there is fewel in us; and ſhould he not tempt us, we ſhould tempt and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke our ſelves hereto; we ſhould ſolicite, and uſe the forcibleſt arguments that might be to ſtir up our baſe natures to proceed from envyings to ſtrife, and from ſtrife to diviſions. How ſecretly doth <hi>Cain</hi> carry fire in his boſome, and he ſtudies and watches a convenient opportunity to poure out his poyſon on his own brother: <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> could not live together. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> could not work together. This is natural to all, its the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fruit proceeding from that root of bitterneſſe in all.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond Argument is taken from Jeſus Chriſt, acting in his offices <hi>for us, to us,</hi> and <hi>in us</hi> for this end, to make up this diviſion made by our ſins, and continued: which if it had not been cauſed by our ſins, the end of his <hi>actions</hi> had been <hi>void.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Acting <hi>for us</hi> as an <hi>interceſſor,</hi> which extends to all that then beleeved, or ſhould hereafter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.20, 21. When he prayes for a poſitive Bleſſing, its likewiſe againſt the curſe and evil in the negative; when he prayes for Unity, he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118256:20"/>prayes againſt diviſion. Sure, as he prayed not in vain to his Father, ſo not for us; <hi>viz.</hi> for a thing we wanted not, or could procure to our ſelves. It was the groan, the longing of our dear Saviour for us, proceeding from an holy Spirit, and bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els filled with compaſſion, grieved for our diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with God, and amongſt our ſelves: and what motion to the contrary is in us, proceeds from a contrary ſpirit to that which was in our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Acting <hi>to us</hi> as a <hi>maſter,</hi> a <hi>preacher</hi> of <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> teaching and inſtructing his people and ſervants according to the will of his heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther revealed to him, and his <hi>fathers</hi> and <hi>his</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. Thus we read Chriſt breathing out of the boſome of his Father his mind to us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44, 45. <hi>But I ſay unto you, Love your enemies, bleſs them that curſe you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them which deſpitefully uſe you, and perſecute you: That ye may be the children of your Father which is in heaven; for he maketh his ſun to riſe on the evil and on the good, and ſendeth rain on the juſt and on the unjuſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Per verba ſcandit oratio, ab affectu ad verba, à verbis ad res ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, &amp;c. <hi>Grot. in loc.</hi>
               </note> There is the Precept teaching us how to demean our ſelves towards them that are out of the Church, how to temper our language, our actions outwardly, nay our prayers to God for them in private, perfumed with this odour of Love. Saint <hi>Luke</hi> doth at large ſet down the ſame in the Affirmative, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 35. <hi>But love ye your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and do good, and lend, hoping for nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: and your reward ſhall be great, and ye ſhall be the children of the moſt high: for he is kind unto
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118256:20"/>the unthankfull, and to the evil.</hi> In the Negative, verſ. 37. <hi>Judge not, and ye ſhall not be judged: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne not, and ye ſhall not be condemned: forgive, and ye ſhall be forgiven.</hi> And couples them ſweetly together, from the great and neer reſemblance hereby they will have of God. Chriſt himſelf comes as a Lamb, in all his preachings labours to work on them humility, innocency, and unity, and propoſes his own pattem for lowlineſs and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the preſervatives of Union; and when he is to leave them in this world, (like <hi>Joſeph</hi> parting with his brethren, <hi>Fall not out by the way,</hi> Gen. 45.24.) leaves this injunction to them as the words of a dying Saviour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.12. <hi>This is my command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That ye love one another, as I have loved you.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>Theſe things I command you, that ye love one another.</hi> And come we a little after him, and hearken to the voice of <hi>John,</hi> his beloved Diſciple, lying in his boſome, and breathing out the mind of his Maſter to us: reade I ſay his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, and you will think him <hi>totus compoſitus ex amore;</hi> Saint<note n="*" place="margin">Beatus <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes</hi> Evan geliſta cum E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſi moraretur uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad ultimam ſenectutem, et vix inter Diſcipulorum manus ad Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam deferre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur, nec poſſit in plura vocem contexere, nihil aliud per ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las proferre col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectas, niſi hoc, Filioli, diligite alterutrum; tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Diſcipuli et fratres, qui aderant, tadio affecti, quod ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſemper au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, dixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, Magiſter, Quare ſemper hoc loqueris? Qui reſpondit (dignam <hi>Joan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> ſententiam) quia praeceptum Domini eſt, et ſi ſolum ſiat, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit. <hi>Hier. in Gal. Com. p. 947.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hierome</hi> hath a relation of him, That when he was ſo weak with age, that he was not able to go to the publique Auditory unſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his Diſciples, and there not to ſpeak much; this was his conſtant Lecture, <hi>Children, Love one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother:</hi> but his Diſciples being wearied with the conſtant repetition of this one thing, ſaid, <hi>Maſter, why alwayes this?</hi> He anſwered, <hi>Becauſe its the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of our Lord Jeſus, and do but this, and it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 In us as a <hi>King,</hi> ruling and guiding his people
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118256:21"/>inwardly, ſubduing their ſins and corruptions. And rules he not as <hi>King of Peace?</hi> And will he then ſuffer theſe unruly luſts of envy and ſtrife to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in us? Will he ſuffer his Subjects to bite and devoure one another? It was for the men poſſeſſed with devils to be rent and torn themſelves, and to fly on ſuch as paſſed by; but not for ſuch in whom Chriſt dwels and rules, ſwayes his Scepter of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and peace. Are not his Laws righteous, and well known before us? Hath he given tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to any <hi>to tolerate diviſion and ſtrife</hi> in his Kingdome? Doth his Spirit by which he rules in us ſet us at variance, or anywhere give the leaſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance to diſſenters? We reade of him, That he only hath power to govern, and that in peace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>For unto us a child is born, unto us a ſon is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the government ſhall be upon his ſhoulder: and his name ſhall be called Wonderfull, Counſeller, The mighty God, The everlaſting Father, The prince of peace.</hi> Then ſtrife and diviſion do diſcover, that ſuch have little intereſt in the <hi>interceſſory prayers</hi> of Chriſt, that they give little heed to his <hi>command and example,</hi> and that they have as little ſhare in him, who <hi>rules</hi> them in <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>unity,</hi> that are his: but that which cauſeth ſtrife &amp; diviſion proceeds from another ſpirit and mind, even from themſelves and Satan; and in no wiſe from him.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The third Argument is taken from the true, proper, and gracious working of the Spirit of God thorow the word on the heart and ſpirit of every one that is <hi>called to believe,</hi> brought out of their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and unregenerate eſtate, and from the general
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118256:21"/>and groſſe ſociety of this world into the <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints and Church-fellowſhip.</hi> Though theſe men be of divers languages and nations, of divers eſtates and conditions, of divers conſtitutions and qualifications, of divers practices and converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; yet it hath the ſelf ſame work upon them all, that are truly converted; I ſay, at their firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, when the high thoughts of the fleſh were brought down, and the ſtrong powers of a carnal mind ſubdued, it brings them in an holy and peaceable ſociety. Many thouſands were conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Peters</hi> Sermons, queſtionleſſe of ſeveral diſpoſitions and natural inclinations, callings, and practices; yet one general frame and heart wrought in them all, by one and the ſelf ſame Spirit, thorow one and the ſelf ſame Word: as we reade, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41: <hi>Then they that gladly received his Word, were baptized: and the ſame day there were added unto them about three thouſand ſouls.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 46. <hi>And they continued daily with one accord in the temple, and breaking bread from houſe to houſe, did eat their meat with gladneſs and ſingleneſſe of heart.</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 32. <hi>And the multitude of them that beleeved, were of one heart, and of one ſoul: neither ſaid any of them, that ought of the things which he poſſeſſed, was his own, but they had all things common.</hi> And no leſſe do all the <hi>promiſes of Chriſt and his Kingdom</hi> aſſuredly portend for his people: as you may reade <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11. Your great ones, the Lion: your cruel ones, perſecutors, the Leopard: your profane ones, your Wolf, and Bear: your wiſe, and ſubtile ones, that ſoreſt hurt the people of God, the Aſpe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118256:22"/>and Cockatrice, all ſhall lie down with the meek ones of Chriſts Kingdom, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6, 7, 8, 9. And <hi>Chap.</hi> 55.12, 13. having ſhewed the irreſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble power and efficacy of his Word: adds, <hi>you ſhall go out with joy, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 61.7. <hi>For confuſion they ſhall rejoyce in their portion:</hi> A diſtinct lot and ſtation; and this they ſhall rejoyce in inſtead of rude and diſordered confuſions, at the pouring forth of the Goſpel-ſpirit. So <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39. <hi>One name,</hi> Zech. 14.9. <hi>They ſhall ſubſcribe freely unto the Lord. They ſhall Covenant with all their hearts. they ſhall be of one lip,</hi> Zeph. 3.9. For what a ſtrange paradox would it be to Chriſtians, <hi>to receive a Goſpel of peace,</hi> that amongſt the true beleivers of <hi>it ſhould ſet fire</hi> to conſume them and the whole Church?</p>
            <p>Nay, let us appeal to the hearts of any true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever, and but a little catechize him; How waſt thou before thy converſion? haughty, litigious, ſcorn'd an affront, impatient in ſufferings, active in broyles, rejoycing in the Churches diſturbances, full of maliciouſneſſe, envying, &amp;c? But how is it now? all the contention thou haſt is in thy own bowels betwixt ſin and grace, and againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of thy brother? And when thou art in a gracious and ſpirituall frame before God, when thou recollecteſt thy ſelf, and applieſt truth home to thy ſelf, is not thy heart broken? couldſt thou not pour forth thy heart upon the Church, from the head to the skirts of Chriſt, to the pooreſt member of his? nay, when thou ſadly reſenteſt the differences of his people, couldſt thou not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118256:22"/>to give them thy blood to joyn and faſten them together, if it could prevaile? Were not then the Saints of God, one that had the leaſt of the image of God, one in whom you could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern any thing of a gracious Spirit, dear and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in thy eyes? and did not grace make a great difference in thy affection, even towards thy own kindred? <hi>Art not thou thus ſtill in the right actings of thy mind and affections?</hi> How is it now that thou divideſt from them, and envieſt, and ſtriveſt with them? What! from the ſame ſpiritual temper? or are thoſe Chriſtians to whom we were joyned in the ſame fellowſhip <hi>apoſtatized from the faith?</hi> No ſure: they are the ſame, but you are not: the Fleſh hath encreaſed on you, and the Spirit but weak in you. Sometimes if thou obſerveſt thy own heart, thou wilt be ready to wrangle with the Lord, as <hi>Jonah,</hi> and <hi>Elias:</hi> and therefore he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries this character on him, That he was a man <hi>ſubject to the like paſsions as we are.</hi> And thou art more ready to vilifie thy brother, in thy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to whet thy tongue (I wiſh they were but ſuddain paſſions) in his neceſſities thou putſt thy hand into thy boſome, or reproacheſt him in his diſtreſſe; and his ſlips are matter of joy and boaſtings to thee: but compare thy ſelf with thy former frame of Spirit, deceive not thy ſelf, look candidly into thy actions, thou ſhalt find no Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel character on them, thy heart and affections much altered, and thou wilt freely confeſſe this comes from thy over-grown carnal heart, from new riſings of old mortified corruptions, and a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118256:23"/>looſing of thoſe Goſpel reins once laid upon thy Soul.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Arg.</hi> It appears that theſe only have the riſe from the praedominant fleſh in us, <hi>From thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and groſſe corruptions that diſcloſe themſelves in the handling and managing of Church-contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Envy.</hi> That is a grievous ſin, but cleerly acting herein; which is an emulating anothers happineſſe,<note place="margin">Invidus alteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us rebus macre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it opimis.</note> glory, proſperity, &amp;c. and ſo much the worſe, to make at the bleſſings and honour of God conferred on his Church. Its the ſad prolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor to many horrid Tragedies; and none ſo deſperate, and dangerous as the envie of friends; for in its execution it loſeth all relations, even of nature it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Ignorance.</hi> Not knowning their own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not the due honour they owe to the members of Chriſt Jeſus in their places; nor ſolidly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the truths of God, &amp;c. elſe, true and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified knowledge would put an end to many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Pride.</hi> They ſuppoſe themſelves ſlighted, and deſerving far more then they have, ſeeing that in ſuch a Church way there will be many that will go before them, out-ſhine him; look upon their own gifts in a Multiplying glaſs, upon the gifts of others at the wrong end of the Proſpective glaſſe; keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no due proportion, and ſpiritual ſobriety in their thoughts of themſelves, and in their wayes and callings over themſelves, in reference to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:118256:23"/>
            <p n="4">4 The continuance in theſe, breeds <hi>a perverſe and ſtubborn ſpirit, will not return:</hi> hating to be thought ignorant, to be adjudged of errour, or guilty of unlawful ſtrivings and diviſions; that which thruſts them upon, keeps them in the way and practicte of Diviſions; and ſeldome do we finde ſuch conſtant to any thing but factions and fractions; and are for any, wherein they may be eminent. Oh it would make a heart to tremble to ſee what an horrid change is wrought in them, what a ſpirit of deep ſlumbring is fallen on them, they lying under the want even of natural light and reaſon.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Coveteouſneſs;</hi> They caſt about for wayes that are profitable and gainful: And when the wayes of Truth become thorny, and dirty, cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, obnoxious to loſſe of place, eſtate, &amp;c. then they muſt divide, as <hi>Demas</hi> leaves <hi>Paul,</hi> and lay out for ſome other courſe, though oppoſite to truth it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Corruption:</hi> An ill judgement, and a worſe affection. Some men love not to live within com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, and by a ſober, ſtrict, and impartial rule; like a diſeaſed man, that is either aſhamed of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or elſe fearful his companions will be aſhamed of him, keeps therefore by himſelf, or aſſociates with his like; an evil and unclean heart will warpe from a pure and watchful Congregation. Theſe and many others being thorowly and impartially weighed, may ſee theſe iniquities eaſily breaking forth, and foſtered in diviſions, and muſt needs ſay, Surely theſe things cannot be from God, but from the fleſh.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118256:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. Envyings, ſtrifes, and diviſions <hi>tend to the maintenance, and ſatisfying of the fleſh;</hi> and as the end is to which any thing directly tends, of the ſame nature are the means; and whatſoever tends not to the glory of God, advancement of the truth, promoting of the Power of Godlineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> cannot proceed from the Spirit but the Fleſh, and theſe lead directly and principally to the pleaſing of the fleſh, and nouriſhment thereof: By <hi>fleſh</hi> I here mean not in a ſtrict ſenſe the touch and ſence of fleſh, and thoſe ſins that are acted by, and terminated in the fleſh, which are properly carnal pleaſures, &amp;c. in which ſence Saint <hi>John</hi> takes it 1 <hi>Joh,</hi> 2. and the<note n="*" place="margin">Peccata reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piunt ſpeciem ex objectis <hi>&amp;c.</hi> illa peccata quae perficiuntur delectatione ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituali, vocan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur pec cata ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualia; illa verò quae perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuntur in dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatione carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, vocantur pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata carnalia. <hi>Aqu. 12. q. 72. a. 2. c.</hi>
               </note> Schoolmen; but that which is commonly called the carnall part, the corrupt, unregenerate, and unmortified part of man in the whole. And this</p>
            <p n="1">1. Tends to the <hi>ſatisfying and delight of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly,</hi> and ſuch as are not only groſſely carnall, but profeſſed enemies to the truth; and herein we act no more for them, then they would do them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; But of this more hereafter; only its a ſign that that beareth much evill in it, that pleaſeth men that are wholly evill, and reliſh nothing elſe, and this not only for them to ſee it in us, but to joyn with parties againſt us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It tends to <hi>a general licentiouſneſs:</hi> men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing their necks from the yoak of Chriſt, run into any way that ſeems good to them; and makes way to an everlaſting evagation; for he that will take liberty to divide from a people walking by Divine Rule in the main, muſt lay down in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118256:24"/>
               <hi>a Principle of unſetlednes, and to have a grant of Liberty</hi> to depart at pleaſure from any elſe that appears not to be more divinely grounded; and ſo like the Traveller, paſſes from one place to another, from one Church to another, for novelty, curioſitie, and ſpeculation ſake; only is not ſo ſure to return to his true home as the Traveller; and this is done for Conſcience ſake. Hereby the hypocrite, the unclean perſon, and weak brother may throw the reins off his neck and return to his vomit, for ſuch ſtand open to temptations; Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom a wanton <hi>head and heart</hi> being ſeparable: if we conſider who are ſubject to this ſad judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, even corrupt people, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. <hi>For of this ſort are they which creep into houſes, and lead cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſilly women laden with ſins, led away with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers luſts,</hi> and what ſuch doth naturally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.16. <hi>But ſhun propha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and vain bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, for they will increaſe unto more ungodlineſs.</hi> and take them at the beſt, (I dare appeal to any true beleever) whether ſince his diviſion, and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving he hath made any<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi adhuc re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidet talis ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, aut nullus eſt aut exiguus Evangelii pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus, <hi>Marl.</hi>
               </note> ſenſible increaſe in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nay, whether he is not leſsned in his love, care, and practice; and its ſeldom with ſuch <hi>ſchiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Non nos ab ill is, ſed illi à nobis receſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt; &amp; cum haereſes &amp; ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata poſtmodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nata ſunt, dum conventicula ſi bi diverſa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituunt, veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis caput, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que orignem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquerunt. <hi>Cypt. de unit. Eccleſ. p. 234.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Volunteers,</hi> but they loſe the very Truth it ſelf; and let any judge how it ſhould be otherwiſe; for theſe meerly tend to confuſion, where there is this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Diviſion,</hi> there will be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no ſtanding order, or <hi>confuſion;</hi> and if any thing can make greater gaps in the hedge of the Vineyard for good to go forth, and evill to enter; if a wider gate can be ſet open for evils in judgement and life,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118256:25"/>it muſt be the gates of Hell; and this we may eaſily judge by what ſucceſs it hath already had even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all parties, and even ſuch that meerly in tenderneſs of conſcience, or deſire of greater per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in holineſs have parted from them.</p>
            <p>Now, if we look upon envyings, ſtrifes, and dl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions breaking firſt out from Satan, by whom the whole world was and is ſet on fire, and iſſuing freely from mans lapſed nature, as to be made up by Chriſt, and wrote againſt by the Goſpel, as maintained by reigning luſts, and maintaining the reign of luſts, it muſt needs prove thus at laſt, that a people beginning, and proceeding herein do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray a carnall minde, if not totally carnall.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cartwright, Ball. Synod againſt Diſſenting <hi>&amp;c. with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
               </note>And whereas there hath been much ſaid in the juſtification of Separation and Diviſion, and much more againſt it, I ſhall ſay little Polemically in this Diſcourſe; only hint an Objection or two briefly with their Anſwers.</p>
            <p>Some from <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.22. gather the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of gathered Churches made up of members rent and divided from others.</p>
            <p>The place makes againſt them; For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That two or three, hath reference to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of a Church, as appears clearly by the context to any intelligent and unbyaſſed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or if in generall it appertains to Chriſtians, yet its ſpoken to ſuch as are ſtill of the ſame Church before ſpoken of, and ſtill preſerve their unity to the whole, notwithſtanding their private aſſembling. <hi>Two or three of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:118256:25"/>
            <p n="3">3 Mark the manner of their meeting; <hi>In my Name:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neſe quidem variâ interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione decipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant &amp;c. oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens non multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudini ſed una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitati depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantium pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum tribui. <hi>Cypr. ib.</hi>
               </note> Can they be gathered in <hi>his Name</hi> that divide the Church and Truth it ſelf? Can they meet <hi>in his Fear</hi> that deſpiſe his Worſhip? Can it be to his glory that labours againſt unity? Let us not deceive our ſelves by falſe gloſſing the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God hears not men of many mouthes, but of one mouth and heart. Others ſay, That God commands them to depart out of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True, ſo you ought in reſpect of your ſpirituall and temporall ſafety,<note place="margin">Non laudamus errones, qui va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur &amp; ad nullam ſe Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam adjungunt, quia nuſquam inveniant ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ideam, in quâ non deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur aliquid in moribus, aut diſciplina; ſed quaeramus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam in qua articuli ſidei recte docentur, &amp; errores non defenduntur, &amp; adha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c nos adjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus, hanc do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem audia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; diliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; noſtram invocationem, &amp; confeſſionem ipſius precibus &amp; confeſſioni aggregemus, <hi>Chem. part 3. de Eccleſ. p. 279.</hi>
               </note> and out of a Church that is <hi>Babyloniſh, Idolatrical,</hi> defiled in the very Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals of Religion, and corrupt in the materials of the Ordinances, from ſuch depart, but not from Churches that every one calls Babyloniſh, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſuch as call it ſo that they might ſet up another of their own; and while you depart from <hi>Babylon</hi> ſo called, take heed you do not really run into <hi>Babylon</hi> its damnable Errors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But where doctrine is ſound according to divine Writ, diſcipline in general pure; No ſuch is <hi>Babylon,</hi> from no ſuch let us depart.</p>
            <p>But the more refined takes offence at our mixed Congregations and ſo depart?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Yea, if they depart becauſe mixed with ſome unſanctified profeſſors (as they judge) and will not joyn with any mixed, they muſt reſolve to be of no conſtituted and particular Church in this world, <hi>no not of Chriſts own,</hi> if he and his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and hearers were now preſent in this world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. However, thou taxeſt many of them to bee carnall, and ſo not to be communicated withall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118256:26"/>in ſuch high and ſpirituall myſteries (which thou canſt never prove); But doſt not thou ſhew thy ſelf to be carnal in ſeparating from the whole, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the corruption of one member,<note place="margin">Sicut ipſi nihil minus quam Dei eccleſia ſunt, ſic corum improbitas Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam non tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit, Eccleſia no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men delere non poteſt, <hi>1 John 2.19.</hi> Neque enim diſſitemur quin nomine Eccleſia, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crita etiam qui in ca ſunt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendantur, dicente Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no &amp;c. <hi>Matth. 13. &amp; 25. Zanch. de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. page 535. lib. 8.</hi>
               </note> and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down this, and ſetting up another?</p>
            <p n="3">3. But doth the Congregation tolerate, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nive at, brook a profane perſon, an obſtinate ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, an ignorant man to communicate with thee? if ſo, then more occaſion to divide:</p>
            <p>But our diviſion is not ſchiſme, or our ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not diviſion, nor proceeds from envying and ſtrife.</p>
            <p>Truly in a <hi>Grammatical ſence,</hi> diviſion muſt bee ſchiſm, and ſeparation muſt be diviſion; but I know it not otherwiſe in your <hi>myſtical ſence;</hi> and I am ſure in a Scriptural and <hi>ſpiritual ſence</hi> it ſhews a carnal minde, and that it doth proceed from a ſpirit of the former temper, even among you of this Citie. I ſhall make it good in the Uſes, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Doctrine in this particular, to the People of this Citie, and in generall to all Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>But before we fall on the Application, take with me theſe Cautions:</p>
            <p n="1">1. I make not every <hi>differing</hi> brother, a <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> brother,<note place="margin">Vide Zanch. de Eccleſ.</note> nor every difference a ground ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for ſtrife or diviſion; and if divided, yet neither Heretique nor Schiſmatique ſo long as the difference is not plainly determined by Scripture, and that the difference doth not evidently make way for dangerous, and more pernicious opinions and practices.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Difference and diviſion, and ſtrife betwixt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118256:26"/>
               <hi>Church and Church in ſeveral Kingdoms,</hi> is not ſo great, or of ſuch evill conſequence and hurtfull, as <hi>in a Church in one Kingdom;</hi> for times, places, and manners may much alter the Government in Churches according to Eccleſiaſtical, nay and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious policy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Difference in theſe dayes <hi>of ours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quod in Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priano naevus, in vobis fuligo, <hi>&amp;c. Aug.</hi> Quod in patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus error, in Armenis Haerc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis. <hi>Cot. Bolt. Arraign. of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> p. <hi>152.</hi>
               </note> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſuch as the men of theſe daies profeſs themſelves, is worſe, and more dangerous, and leſſe tolerable then in any daies and times before; for the greater light, the greater love; more Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, more peace ſhould be.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That ſmaller differences when under the Name of Chriſt, this for him, and that againſt him, when really he is not concerned in them, but the very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopting him Patron of them, makes them dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly conſequential, higher, and leſſe reconcileable; for they moſt engage conſcience, provoke zeal.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That differences taking on them (as truly moſt do) <hi>the name of men,</hi> and ſo gathering into divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Churches, as well as diſtinguiſhing names, do declare them to be evill,<note place="margin">Hinc Tertullia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtae, Origini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtae, &amp;c. Sic Browniſtae, &amp;c. etiam Jeſuitae, &amp;c.</note> and proceed from carnal principles; for elſe all Truth, and waies meet in Chriſt, whoſe name we have owned, and glory in alone, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſtians; and more palpable are they that aſſume ſtrange arrogant names to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which beſpeaks nothing more then pride, envie, diviſion, eſpecially theſe being in one Church and that a reformed one.</p>
            <p>Theſe premiſed, which you ought to take along with you to allay ſometimes the bitterneſs of ſpeech (if there be any) for I direct not this to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118256:27"/>Heretiques ſealed under a judgement to the laſt day, but <hi>to men, to Chriſtians</hi> who were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by the ſame means, nouriſhed and brought up in the ſame ordinance, whoſe affections burned as they walked together in the houſe of God, and never more happy then in their publike and private meetings; but now eſtranged, if not envying, ſtrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, dividing like enemies, as if there was now no peace to be had with the <hi>old Puritan</hi> as in former times; againſt you muſt I make good this charge of the Apoſtle, and herein I muſt be plain, and if I be ſharp, if too ſharp, I cannot be ſo ſharp with you as you are one with another;<note place="margin">Non omnis qui parcit amicus, nec qui verbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat inimicus. <hi>Aug. unit. ep. 48.</hi>
               </note> and happily I may be, and prove a better friend to you that call you <hi>carnal,</hi> then he that calls you <hi>Saints,</hi> and a check in the mouth is fitter for you then a ſtroke under the chin.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Doe not your ſtrifes and diviſions ariſe from Envyings? not to meddle with your State diviſions, your boaſting of triumphant and victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enterprizes, your diſ-officing, nay and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of one another (though theſe fall under my cognizance, and take their riſe from your diſ-a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements in opinion about religion) but only in point of Religion. What means your depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not only of one Government, but all <hi>kinds of Government ſucceſsively,</hi> as it hath grated on your evill humours, but of perſons of honour, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown, religion, moſt tender conſciences, of unſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lives, zealous Martyrs for the truth, laying ſad reproaches and aſperſions on them in your Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets we read in the Country? What means thoſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:118256:27"/>ridiculous and abſurd retrolocutions, calling good evill, and evill good, bitter ſweet, and ſweet bitter, liberty thraldome, and thraldom liberty, falſitie fidelitie, and fidelity falſity, backſliding conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and conſtancie backſliding, true zeal ſedition, and ſedition true zeal? Whence are thoſe ſelf-admirations, hyperbolicall jactations, worſe then the very Heathen Philoſopher, that would not take the name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? What mean your ſeveral cries in the City, and Congregations, ſetting up <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, and <hi>Apollos</hi> Church, and <hi>Cephas</hi> his Church, and this the holyeſt, and that the pureſt, the heavenlieſt Church? come not theſe from envious emulations? if from love, I am ſure it hath not the characters the Apoſtle in this Epiſtle attributes to it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. Firſt, he ſhews how far a man may act (as is thought in a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table way) without charity. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1, 2, 3. <hi>Though I ſpeak with the tongues of men and angels, and have not charity, I am become as ſounding braſſe or a tink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling cymbal. And though I have the gift of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, and underſtand all myſteries and all knowledg: and though I have all faith, ſo that I could remove mountains, and have no charitie, I am nothing. And though I beſtow all my goods to feed the poor, and though I give my body to be burned, and have not charity, it profiteth me nothing.</hi> Then what true charity amongſt the members of the Lord Jeſus will do, and will not do: <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4, 5, 6. <hi>Charity ſuffereth long, and is kind: charitie envieth not: charity vaunteth not it ſelf, is not puffed up, Doth not behave it ſelf unſeemly, ſeeketh not her
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118256:28"/>own, is not eaſily provoked, thinketh no evill, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth not in iniquitie, but rejoyceth in the truth:</hi> I confeſſe in your way you ſhew forth much of the firſt in gifts, elocutions, prophecies, &amp;c. but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in charity (unleſs I belie my knowledge and conſcience) ſay that you ſuffer long, that you are kinde, that you envie not, that you vaunt not, that you are not puffed up, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which things muſt needs deſtroy the ſociety and communion of the Saints of God, and ſure that is not charity; No, no, thy envyings, ſtrifes, and diviſions, teſtifie to thy face O <hi>London,</hi> and we in the Country can witneſſe againſt thee; for though thy diviſions at firſt aroſe like a <hi>ſmall handed cloud,</hi> now it hath quite <hi>ſpread</hi> over thee, and have been the <hi>heavieſt hand</hi> that ever thou bareſt; nay, and they have ſpread over us too; the <hi>ſparks,</hi> the flames of thy fire in whole ſheets have light on our Houſes and Towns: Whence have come any Emiſſaries to broach their dark lights, and infatuating opinions to divide our Congregations, but out of <hi>London?</hi> and theſe not only come with thy opinions, but with the ſame or more bitter, invective, ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and reproachfull languages, then we read in thy Satyricall toy-books, as if in the next Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they were reprinted on their breſts, with their amendments: So that the <hi>Vipers</hi> bred in thy bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els and have even conſumed thee, now <hi>creep</hi> into ours.</p>
            <p>And to manifeſt the coldneſs of your affections, that you deſire ſtill to live in the fire, and that peace is not in your hearts, lo your earneſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118256:28"/>for a toleration, not a bare connivance, but a command to divide; lo your writings againſt the reſtraint of all evils, of any evils, that ſo you may proceed to a <hi>Mathematical diviſion.</hi> Some ſaying, I can live and keep my conſcience amongſt any; and ſo I have my liberty, I care not what the reſt be; this Conſcience is not ſuch a one as <hi>Lots,</hi> as <hi>Davids;</hi> but he that can live in <hi>Sodome</hi> with them, may come to live in <hi>Hell</hi> with them; and this mans conſcience cannot endure to have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with <hi>a weak brother,</hi> that can live with comfort and reſt amongſt men as ill <hi>as Devils:</hi> And others flie in the face of juſtice with perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of Goverment with Antichriſtianiſme. What ailes theſe lowings of Oxen, and bleatings of Sheep? but envyings, ſtrifes, and diviſions; and ſuch as are unchriſtian, fleſhly, devilliſh; even ſuch (if they be not ſuddainly reconciled or abated) will conſume you: And as for my part, I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you were cold, then luke-warm, and that an impious Sect, and Errour was ſolely maintained, and Truth it ſelf perſecuted, then all Errors tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated.</p>
            <p>I will not enlarge my ſelf further, leaſt while I ſpeak againſt diviſion,<note place="margin">Homicidae ſunt apud Deum ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les &amp;c. &amp; cum nobis ſemel mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricudum ſit, illi tamen &amp; odio, &amp; verbis &amp; delictis ſuis quotidic peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munt. <hi>Cypr. Ep 55. p. 102.</hi>
               </note> you ſay I have no deſire to Union; only let me tell you that you are ſet on fire of hell; and you are of that evill one, that was a murtherer, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. and though you do not actually ſlay, burn, and eat up one another, yet by degrees you are conſuming one another, and in a <hi>degree murthering one another, putting them to death daily, whom nature hath ordered but once to die,</hi> and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118256:29"/>no marvel that St. <hi>James</hi> calls it diveliſh, and the fire is brought from hell, when as theſe ſad envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings beſeem rather the damned in hell, then the people of God on earth; for the happines of Gods Church ſhall be an aggravation to the miſeries in in hell, and their glory the damneds envy, their triumph the damneds terror, to which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our thus ſpeaks, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.28. <hi>There ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, when yee ſhall ſee Abraham, and Iſaac, and Jacob, and all the Prophets in the kingdome of God, and you your ſelves thurſt out.</hi> When they ſhall <hi>ſee them</hi> thus and thus,<note place="margin">Stridor denti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um opus eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidiae.</note> whoſe goodnes and grace they mocked at on earth, their glory in heaven ſuch will envy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I muſt now tell you, that theſe things being ſo evident, that you are carnal; boaſt not of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as if you had it, and none elſe, and therefore ye depart from the Antichriſtian Congregations: True, if they were ſo cleerly proved by Text of Scripture, it were good to divide; but do not you ſay ſo of them that you might juſtifie your diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſtill nouriſh your envious ſtrivings? but I ſay boaſt not of the Spirit, its not a ſpirit of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, but it meekens mens ſpirits; its not a ſpirit of ſtriving, but ſtirreth up to the aſſiſtance one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; not a ſpirit of diviſion, but unites the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Jeſus Chriſt with the ſtrongeſt bonds that any ſociety or body can be united withall;<note place="margin">Qui ſectarii ſunt, licet vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur eſſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualiſſimi, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra tamen carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les exiſtunt. <hi>Muſc. in loc. p. 81.</hi>
               </note> boaſt not of the Goſpel, its not a Goſpel of contention, but reconciliation; not of diviſion, but calls all true beleevers into one communion and ſpirituall fellowſhip; <hi>boaſt not that you are the ſpiritual ones,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118256:29"/>when no wayes more then yours diſcover carnality.</hi> And its a ſhame, nay it will be a greater condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to this Citie to be <hi>yet carnal,</hi> then for <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaida</hi> and <hi>Chorazin</hi> not to beleeve; you ſeemed to beleeve, to repent, to embrace your faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with joy, and to make your Citie their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, who were your Cities glory; to ſave their lives who ſpend their lives on you and for you, who have been ſuch glorious lights in your firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that have made you to out-ſhine other Cities, and encreaſed your glory to a greater degree be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what it hath been ever ſince it was a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and you have had many of theſe Miniſters faithfull, laborious, godly, learned, who for their paucity ſeemed but the gleanings of this Church, yet better then the Vintage of the whole; and <hi>yet carnall?</hi> You again reciprocally followed them, maintained them, rejoyced in their doctrine, then laboured for their unity in the whole City; and to theſe adde, you ſuffered with them, and you were ready to break the ice for them that ſhould have led you into the water; and <hi>yet carnal?</hi> What, the very Head of this Nation ſick, rent, cut a pieces, one piece of it falling this way, another that, a third a third way, wherein there is little love, no reſt, no eaſe night nor day, and having ſo many Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians with ſuch admirable balm to apply? True, thy wounds and diſeaſes are great and have fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred long, inſomuch that they have infected the whole, and ſtink in the noſtrils of thy ſiſter Churches; but are theſe wounds incurable, theſe breaches, theſe diviſions irreconcileable? True, it
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:118256:30"/>may be the dividing opinions are; but are the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Chriſtians? I muſt tell thee <hi>London,</hi> thou art ungratefull to thy Miniſters, to thy God, and badly requiteſt him for his gracious protections, Chriſt Jeſus for his Goſpel-adminiſtrations; that when he hath delivered thee from thy former yoke, thou ſhouldſt throw off his own yoke, and when he made an open way of a full union in the whole Church by his bleſſed mercies, and you to break yours aſunder, ſure you are and were of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and unmortified hearts, which otherwiſe in theſe times would not ſo fully diſcover themſelves, being like <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> Image one part falling from another, becauſe uncementable, being of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall tempers and natures; if it be that you are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, you will mourn for the diviſions of the Church, labour to reunite and re-allie the forces of Gods people, which by ſuch as you are thus ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and thus divided;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> My next endeavour is, (after the making good of the charge) to work ſome remedie for the crime, to extinguiſh the fire of envy, to take off the edge of ſtrife, and to reconcile theſe carnall and dangerous diviſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By ſhewing you the cauſes why we re-unite not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By intermixing remedies with the cauſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By propoſing ſome motives to make them effectuall to us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the two firſt fall in together; we ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn the meanes to remedie the evill under each particular; its a thing hath been much endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:118256:30"/>by many far more learned and judicious then my ſelf; its a thing ſo deſireable, ſo amiable, that its worth every mans prayer and work; a thing that gives occaſion of great joy, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Wee are bound to thank God alwayes for you, brethren, as it is meet, becauſe that your faith groweth exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and the charity of every one of you all towards each other aboundeth.</hi> Unity, peace, what ſweet and comfortable words they are? but as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant drops of rain (though ſmall) do more refri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerate and refreſh the hot and parched earth, then the ſudden daſhes of rain; let my ſmall drop fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their ſweet and pleaſant ſhowrs; it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute as much as a drop can do to this barren and thornie Church of ours.</p>
            <p>You heard before that a carnal minde is the cauſe of theſe; That <hi>Satan, Hereticks, Jeſuites,</hi> &amp;c. are great promoters and aggravators of theſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; But to paſſe by theſe, I ſpeak to them that have been and may ſtill ſeem to be in and of the Church of Chriſt, and the hinderances of union lies on the ſcore</p>
            <p>Of the
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>People.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Of the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> whoſe duty it is to be ſo farre from ſcattering <hi>coals</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and throwing in their bones of <hi>diviſion,</hi> that they ſhould be one of the <hi>filii olei</hi> on the left hand of the Candleſtick, to ſpeak peace unto her, and put forth her fires; but the reaſon why they abide ſtill divided, and ſtand farre off from one another,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:118256:31"/>nay, in part Adverſaries, is, becauſe</p>
            <p>Of an
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Unwiſe</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cowardly</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Self-intereſted</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. An <hi>Unwiſe Magiſtrate</hi> that knows not that it is his duty to look after the peace of the Church as well as of your Common-wealth, when need requires, and in Policie he might labour for that Eccleſiaſticall Unity, being a great preferva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to his juſt authority, and is ſure to rule well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them that are pure, peaceable, conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: And truly it is a moſt ſad thing to have men more rich then wiſe, more popular then religious to rule over us, that know not what duty they owe to <hi>God in the Church,</hi> as well as <hi>of the Church in the Common wealth.</hi> But will you underſtand, is it perſecution to doe juſtice, or is there any juſtice for a wronged, a defiled Church? Are not<note n="*" place="margin">Non diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guendum eſt ubi Scriptura non diſtinguit. <hi>Bolt. Arraign. of Error</hi> in loc. <hi>Rom. 13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>all evill doers</hi> to be puniſhed? is not ſin that is indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and made cleer ſo to be, to be prohibited? is this to offend and force conſcience (that only falls under the power of God)<note n="*" place="margin">Si quae igitur adverſus vos le ges conſtitutae ſunt, non bene facere cogimi ni, ſed malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere prohibemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. <hi>Aug. cont. lit. Petil. l. 2. cap. 38.</hi>
               </note> to hinder the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick profeſſion of that which is evill? Have any power to <hi>grant a Toleration</hi> to all Religions, and not a power to <hi>reſtrain any?</hi> or can you lawfully <hi>confirm any,</hi> and <hi>diſſolve none?</hi> Is Chriſt in the <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> more to be protected and cared for then Chriſt in the <hi>ſubſtance?</hi> and are Kings and Princes more to adore and ſerve Chriſt <hi>coming,</hi> then Chriſt <hi>come?</hi> Cannot his <hi>Goſpel</hi> challenge your ſword as well as his <hi>Law?</hi> and becauſe the equity and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the generall precept is not clear enough to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118256:31"/>you, do you expect divine particular inſtructions under the Goſpel? or is it a leſſe ſin to be a <hi>falſe Apoſtle,</hi> then a <hi>falſe Prophet?</hi> Know you not that the <hi>winepreſſe</hi> as well as the <hi>watch-tower</hi> is ſet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the hedge of the Vineyard? or do ye expect that God ſhould immediately from heaven, declare his diſlike of ſuch evil doings, execute juſtice, ſtrike them with <hi>blindnes,</hi> or caſt them into a bed of <hi>ſicknes?</hi> if you were not Chriſtians, you might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it; or if your Chriſtian eyes were open, you might ſee very much to convince you herein in fearfull examples.</p>
            <p>Be wiſe then O ye Judges, and kiſſe the Son with honour and reverence; offer to your King all you have; your <hi>golden Scepter</hi> as well as your <hi>Box of Myrrh</hi> and ointments; your <hi>ſword,</hi> your glittering ſharp ſword as well as you <hi>glorious Scepter;</hi> and know that Chriſt calls for this now, and will once require an account for the uſe of all he hath given unto you: And lo then (if you be wiſe) the child Jeſus ſwadled in his Truth and Government is laid before you; The Harlot cryes <hi>divide him, divide him;</hi> the true mother falls down at your feet, weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and beſeeching you for the Lords ſake not to <hi>cut him, not to divide him,</hi> let her have him whole all, or none; Is there not a wiſe man amongſt you to decide this?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>cowardly Magiſtrate</hi> that is ſo wiſe to underſtand this, yet he would be as wiſe as to ſave himſelf, he is afraid of a frown; their threats that maintain diviſion are high and lofty, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in power; and its good to act within a ſafe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118256:32"/>line, and to dare no further then we may ſafely returne; its good to walk on fairly in a Magiſtrates pace, and take notice of none on either ſide; let them alone and part themſelves; he that thruſts in betwixt two,<note place="margin">Nec Chriſtiani ultrà aut dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re aut eſſe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus, ſi ad hoc ventum eſt, ut perditorum mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas atque inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias pertimeſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>Cypr. Ep. ad Corn.</hi>
               </note> oft hath the moſt blows and the leaſt thanks; and ſo the truth lies ſhred on the ground, trodden on, and none will <hi>gather it up.</hi> Oh where is the publick ſpirit fit for ſuch a publick perſon? Did <hi>Moſes, Nehemiah, &amp;c.</hi> fear their lives in reſiſting and puniſhing a people deparing from God? Know, that the Lord threatens ſuch as doe remove the bounds, <hi>Limites Eccleſiaſticos:</hi> (<hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.10. <hi>The Princes of Judah were like them that remove the bound: therefore I will pour out my wrath upon them like water.</hi>) and ſuch as doe not with might and main maintain the truth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.3. <hi>Jehu</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> had other ſpirits, and in this reſpect (though the one good and the other bad) put on the ſame ſpirit, both being publick perſons, publickly ſhewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the front of Gods people againſt the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Church.<note place="margin">1 Kings 19.14. 2 Kings 10.16</note> God equally ſtood towards them both, in calling them to publick offices; his cauſe equally concerned them both according to their places, and they both acted according to their capacities: <hi>Jehus ſword</hi> was to be as keen as <hi>Eliahs tongue:</hi> but the Lord grant that our tongues be not ſo much the more too ſharp with ſome, by how much the more the Magiſtrates ſword is too dull.</p>
            <p>Do you expect that the Lord ſhould not act for himſelf yet? if he do, look that you taſte deep in the cup of aſtoniſhment, and that you muſt bear the heavier for your toleration, your cowardly
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:118256:32"/>and ignoble ſpirits. With a very little variation, if and at all, is that true in this ſence; <hi>Iſai.</hi> 59.16. <hi>And hee ſaw that there was no man, and wondred that there was no interceſſour: therefore his arm brought ſalvation unto him, and his righteouſneſſe, it ſuſtained him.</hi> No man ſtepping in betwixt God and the people; not a <hi>Moſes</hi> eminent for acts of <hi>prayer,</hi> not a <hi>Phinehas</hi> with his act of <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe;</hi> its well if you have yet left an <hi>Elias</hi> to <hi>pray and preach to you,</hi> to help to pull down that untem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered morter wherewith others build; elſe it might ſtand (ſo long as it could ſtand) for ſuch poor and weak ſpirited Magiſtrates, and there would not then be a people in the world more miſerable then you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>ſelf-intereſted Magiſtrate;</hi> as for thoſe particular Intereſts, what they are, and how deep they may be laid by the Magiſtrates in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſhall not be nominated, to avoid offences; But whereſoever a Magiſtrate is <hi>co-ingaged,</hi> or <hi>co-inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> a people with himſelf, there their ſecular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects will draw them to ſatisfie that people in all accommodations that may conſiſt with their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and honour, nay and ſometimes againſt their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. This was too much in the Primitive Church; and it was an argument that the Parliament once took up in one of their Declarations againſt their late King, <hi>That he muſt (though himſelf ſhould bee no Papiſt) congratulate the Papiſts in the free uſe of their religion, for the ſervice they then did him;</hi> this is it that hinders union, that ſtrengthens divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, when ſuch as theſe ſide into parties, and help on the diviſion.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:118256:33"/>
            <p>Thoſe that cannot <hi>deny</hi> themſelves, cannot <hi>affirm</hi> Chriſt or his Truth; and what worldly thing ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſwayes in the heart, it will flect and carry moſt powerfully the whole man after it into any party whatſoever; ſo <hi>Judas</hi> leaving the Apoſtles to ſit down with the Scribes and Phariſees, who ever thought to have ſeen him in their Councel? Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories are plentifull in ſuch examples. He that ſets not <hi>Gods glory</hi> in the <hi>top of his aimes,</hi> will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be found thorowly faithfull to the <hi>cauſe of God;</hi> hence is that exhortation <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.3, 4. <hi>Let nothing be done through ſtrife, or vain-glory, but in lowlineſs of minde let each eſteem other better then themſelves. Look not every man on his own things, but every man alſo on the things of others.</hi> Mark how ſubordinately he ſets the directions; Firſt, let all your actions publick and private, ſent of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but love to the Church of God. 2. Then love not your ſelves, but ſometimes wave your own things, and place the things of others in their room, in your minde, deſire, and chief aimes: For as<note n="*" place="margin">Ex codem fonte huc uſque diſſidia continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ata, &amp; nunc acerbius quam uſquam, &amp; plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra quam uſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; abſurdiora quam uſquam falſa dogmata defenduntur. <hi>Zanch. in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Zanchie</hi> well obſerves, That though ſuch may favour others for their own reſpects, yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in that and in all things elſe, that ſinfull ſelf-love ſhall eat up, as the lean Kine did the fat, all that truly makes to the welfare and peace of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and this hath been and ſtill is, in civill and military Magiſtrates the cauſe of much envying, ſtrife, and great diviſions; above all men a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate ſhould leaſt <hi>love himſelf,</hi> and bee like the higheſt bough of the tree, hung with bunches of fruit, dropping into the mouths and skirts of them
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:118256:33"/>that are before him; for him to love himſelf, is for the Sun to be the darkeſt. Make then other mens buſines your own, for you are Magiſtrates not for your ſelves, but them; and labour to ſtrike into thoſe buſineſſe that are in your ſphere, wherein you may honour God moſt, bearing that Motto in your minde, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. <hi>Wherefore the Lord God of Iſrael ſaith, I ſaid indeed, that thy houſe, and the houſe of thy father ſhould walk before me for ever: but now the Lord ſaith, Be it far from me; for them that honour me, I will honour, and they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteemed.</hi> Well then, if we had a Magiſtracy <hi>wiſe,</hi> that could <hi>underſtand;</hi> or <hi>unby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſed,</hi> that would <hi>underſtand;</hi> and <hi>couragious,</hi> to act according to what they <hi>underſtand,</hi> we ſhould ſee truth waited on with peace and righteouſneſſe, and the lovers of truth live comfortably and rejoycing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the <hi>breſts</hi> of Kings and Princes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As touching the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> ſomething is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe in them, nay ſome a chief cauſe hereof; though I think it was beſide their intention, and ſome would now have wiſht to have burnt in the flames of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution before theſe times, or been buried in the greedy Seas, rather then they ſhould eſcape one fire to kindle a worſe. Yet ſome there are whoſe hearts rejoyce that they have brought their divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to this perfection. Who would have rejoyced in the expectation of theſe times ten yeers ſince, if one ſhould have aſcertained them of ſo great a Reformation? and when even now they had their deſires, they exceedingly loathed them. A word to theſe <hi>in reference</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:118256:34"/>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>To themſelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>To others.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. To ſuch as have undertaken the calling of the Miniſtry, as concerning themſelves, their <hi>diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> have bin the <hi>worſt</hi> of all diviſions; their <hi>ſchiſms</hi> look like <hi>hereſies,</hi> and their <hi>ſtrifes</hi> like <hi>waves;</hi> theirs are examplary; when the chief parts of the body are diſtempered, all the reſt muſt needs bee grievouſly affected and afflicted. To you thus;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Take heed of the humour of <hi>Diotrephes;</hi> if the Church do not give thee that honour and reſpect thou judgeſt fit for thy ſelf, and worthy of thee, do not ſtraight quarrel with the Church, reproach, and diſcredit it, and then caſt out for another way wherein thou maiſt be more eminent, and have a party that will cry thee up. Of ſuch the Apoſtle forewarned, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.30. <hi>Alſo of your own ſelves ſhall men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way diſciples after them;</hi> whereon ſaith <hi>Calvin in loc. Ambitio eſt mater omnium haereſe</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. and ſo of ſtrife, envy, and theſe diviſions of fond diſputes to ſeem ſome body, perverſe and froward in their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us therefore in the fear of God prefer one another, give the right hand of fellowſhip one to another; be tender of one anothers honour, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to caſt the mantle over thy brothers infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; be every man as in the Sanctuary, content to be <hi>ſet in his own order,</hi> and ſtand like the fixed ſtars in the Firmament, though all having not the like glory, yet preſerving one another in his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Let us not be too confident of our <hi>private
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:118256:34"/>judgements,</hi> but enquire of <hi>others,</hi> and yeeld, or at the leaſt ſuſpend thy own from the publick, if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the determination of many holy, gracious, and learned men; let us take unto our ſelves the rule of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.23, 24, 25. <hi>But fooliſh and unlearned queſtions avoid, knowing that they do gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſtrifes. And the ſervant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive: but be gentle unto all men, apt to teach, patient: In meekneſs inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them repentance to the acknowledging of the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. So far as you agree, <hi>practice together,</hi> that you may be <hi>fellow labourers;</hi> mutual undertakings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly bind the hearts and affections of men in all callings, and engage us to mutuall aſſiſtance.<note place="margin">Babing. in Exod.</note> The Church is a ſhip, ſaith one, the Spirit the Steerman, the Miniſters as the Oares, that muſt <hi>lift together,</hi> and <hi>ſtrike together,</hi> if they will have the Ship to ſpeed well. Friends that walk to one journies end, will <hi>walk together</hi> as much as may be, meet as oft as may be; our <hi>ends</hi> carrie the ſame pretences; why walke we <hi>two waies?</hi> keep not aſunder in <hi>all,</hi> becauſe of <hi>ſome</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences.</p>
            <p>Therefore take heed that your Ink be not mixed with <hi>gall,</hi> though ſometimes with vinegar; let not the leaſt of the poiſon of Aſpes lie under your tongues; a little thing will keep them from union that have walked abroad at large and have no mind to return: Its the ſtrangeſt thing and moſt diſhonourable for ſuch as we to diſagree; we ſee if Captains fall out, their Souldiers will ſide right or
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:118256:35"/>wrong: I wiſh it was not ſo in the Church. Let us ſtrive to keep as cloſe as we can together, to lay aſide as much of our ſelves as we can; however to walk ſo farre as we may ſafely together, and wait till the Lord ſhall <hi>reveal</hi> the reſt unto us. Thus much concerning our ſelves one to another.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In reference to the Church;</hi> let the peace and union of others be deare to us; to whom ſhould it be precious if not to us, who have charge over them in the Lord? and for this end,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Urge this <hi>Doctrine</hi> much on them, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to our <hi>fellowſhip,</hi> and the Articles of our <hi>Creed,</hi> and a truth ſo much inculcated in Scripture.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be <hi>Catechizing</hi> much, a duty much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to us by the reverend Synod; its well if it were ſet up. Do ſuch as are well grounded in the faith backſlide and divide from the Church? very few; moſt returne: yet ſome there muſt be for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to them that ſtand; for above 900 yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt this duty was much exerciſed, and then neglected,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Mr</hi> Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhel his Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citat. on <hi>Mal.</hi> joyned to <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. p.</hi> 36.37.</note> till the riſing up of <hi>Luther;</hi> and <hi>King</hi> James <hi>tells us, that the reaſon why ſo many fell into Popery and errors, was, their ungroundedneſſe in the points of Catechiſme:</hi> and it was ſtrictly enjoyned, but looſely obſerved in the Church, when over much raſhneſſe overſpread this Kingdome. The Miniſter that uſes it, ſhall find as much comfort in his people as they benefit by him. The Apoſtle takes this courſe, conſidering the weakneſſe of his people, <hi>ver.</hi> 1 <hi>hujus Capitis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>he fed them with milk,</hi> or as it is in the Originall, gave them <hi>milk to drink,</hi> becauſe of their carnall minds; that is, he inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:118256:35"/>them in the plain foundations of Chriſtianity; ſuch as contained enough to ſave them; and very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difying and wholeſome Truths; he did as a good Schoolmaſter, layes a good foundation in Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar; for when they hoiſt them up into books high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then they can well digeſt, they neither under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, nor any whit benefit; but are confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ignorant, proud, and ordinarily run into Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar Errors. For the Apoſtle kept not <hi>ſtrong meat</hi> from them to wrong them, but becauſe they were not fit for it, and ſo might do them more hurt then good; puffe them up, and make them ſeem know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians, when they know nothing as they ought; <hi>viz.</hi> whats that judgement of method, and underſtanding of ſence, as become ſolid and ſober Chriſtians: and thus the Apoſtle deals with the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> he brings them back to the place in Chriſtianity where they began, and makes them Chriſtian Abcedarians again, beginning at the <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> the <hi>rudiments,</hi> or <hi>principles</hi> (as the word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies in the heathen Authors) or <hi>affections</hi> of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12.13. <hi>For when for the time ye ought to be teachers, ye have need that one teach you again which be the firſt principles of the oracles of God, and are become ſuch as have need of milk, and not of ſtrong meat. For every one that uſeth milk, is unskilfull in the word of righteouſneſſe for he is a babe.</hi> This is a ſafe and ſure way to lay a good foundation, and make them fit for great proficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the School of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let them that receive members divided from others, take the Apoſtles caveat, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10.<note n="*" place="margin">Monentur ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que doctores, ut inter docendum reſpectum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmorum habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant illis ſe in omnibus &amp; verbis, &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinae, &amp; vitae moribus accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modent, &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſe captui attemperent, ut ab elementis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiant, nec alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us conſeendant, quam ſequi poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt, ut denique paulatim diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let doctrinam, ne largius infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa ſuperfluat, ut eos omnes, &amp;c. <hi>Marl. in 1 Cor. 1.2.2.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Elementa initii. <hi>Par.</hi> Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimenta, quia ſunt pro rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. Primordia vel initia Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiani.</note>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:118256:36"/>
               <hi>According to the grace of God which is given unto me, as a wiſe maſter-builder I have laid the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and another buildeth thereon. But let every man take heed how he buildeth thereupon.</hi> For as <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. <hi>They were labourers together with God,</hi> and begun a good foundation for a glorious frame of grace; now they come to you, take heed, build ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the good foundation laid and begun; elſe you may ſpoil them in reſpect of what is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy wrought, and of what ſhall be wrought.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Countenance them not in their fooliſh <hi>wrangling queſtions,</hi> either in things beyond them, or beſide them, eſpecially in the unravelling of them, there being no profitableneſſe: and let not acceptance and encouragement be given of thee to any that out of wantonneſſe, curioſity <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from an holy and conſcionable miniſtry unto thy own, unleſſe it be upon <hi>extraordinary</hi> and unuſuall <hi>occaſions,</hi> ſuch as Chriſtian liberty al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and wiſdome may make uſe of without ſcandal. Do not quarrell, but check them, for I know no miniſter but he deſireth to be deare in the eyes of the godly, and much in their thoughts and prayers; onely he would have himſelf ſo ſet up in others, that his love ſhould not procure anothers hate, his honour anothers ſhame, his reſpect ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſlight; no, but would have a fellow-ſharing with all in the hearts of all, therefore he would give to all their ſhare, and not impropriate others hearers to be his followers; and chiefly make them Chriſts: ſo let every miniſter deny his own name, and not gather any to cry up his name, as
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:118256:36"/>
               <hi>John</hi> did in <hi>John</hi> 1.23. <hi>He ſaid I am the voice of one crying in the wilderneſſe, Make ſtraight the way of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. If thou doſt reſolve their quaeries and niceties, let them be according to the Apoſtles rule, in the <hi>evident power and ſtrength of ſpirituall reaſon,</hi> and in the <hi>Authority</hi> of his <hi>miniſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Let him labour to preſerve his <hi>own peace and unity among them</hi> over which the Lord hath ſet him; for many corrupt men out of envy and diſlike to ſuch particular perſons, do divide from their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations; and at the beſt, if thou be at juſt diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with them, thy exhortations to peace can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be well taken, where they ſee contrary actions; men loving to have the double light of life and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine going before them, and many being willing to find out ſtumbling blocks for themſelves in the wayes of God. Follow peace with all men; if poſſible, labour to preſerve it; avoid juſt occaſions; be apt to put up injuries; flee ſuits, and contentions; Lord it not over them, that they may ſee thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is after unity and peace, thy actions being the reall proof, and teſtimonies of thy exhortation; for want of the practiſe of theſe and ſuch like rules, much is added to our diviſions.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the <hi>people</hi> are a grand cauſe of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, and this is moſt apparent out of the Text. We ſee here <hi>Paul</hi> pleads for himſelf, and throws away all his followers; and he taxes no miniſters elſe as deſiring or labouring after any ſuch thing: but wholly and onely charges it upon the ſcore of the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> it were they that envied, and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:118256:37"/>amongſt themſeves: ſome for <hi>Paul,</hi> others for <hi>Apollos,</hi> a third party for <hi>Cephas,</hi> without their ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for. Now briefly (becauſe we have ſpoken to this ſomething already) to ſhew you ſome other grounds of the peoples prompt, and ready ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring themſelves;</p>
            <p n="1">1. From The too much <hi>affectation</hi> of the <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar gifts</hi> of this man above another; therefore they cry him up above another, and reſolve to follow him and none other.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Know, that thou oughteſt not to have thy <hi>admiration</hi> drawn to any <hi>perſons</hi> by their gifts, or any other wayes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That thou haſt (if a member of Chriſt) an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> in all their <hi>gifts,</hi> and equally ſharing in one as well as another, and all ſent and given for thee; not this man alone, but this, and that, &amp;c. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Unto me who am the leaſt of all ſaints, is this grace given, that I ſhould preach among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles the unſearchable riches of Chriſt; In whom we have boldneſſe and acceſſe with confidence by faith in him.</hi> 1 Cor. 3.22. <hi>Whether Paul, or Apollo, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things preſent, or things to come, all are yours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. From a <hi>Zealous affection</hi> he beares to him whom God hath made moſt <hi>inſtrumentall for his good</hi> in the exerciſing of theſe gifts; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore looks on it as his bounden duty to own him, admire him, and follow him before another: he does (as he thinks) out of a pious, and due eſteem of him.</p>
            <p>Know therefore, 1. That it is <hi>not his gifts</hi> that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:118256:37"/>hath wrought this in thee, or for thee, but the grace of God through them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Lord if he had pleaſed, <hi>could have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi> another for the work, and endowed the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of his creatures with power ſufficient to effect this.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hereby thou mayeſt <hi>take</hi> too much from God, and attribute it to the inſtrument by himſelf: and though thou thinkeſt otherwiſe, and denyeſt it, yet God will not part with the glory of thy words, and actions, as well as of thy inward eſteem.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Thou mayeſt love him with an <hi>higher degree</hi> of love then another, but not with <hi>another</hi> love.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Another may be <hi>uſeful</hi> and <hi>ſerviceable</hi> for thee in another eſtate, as he in this. Its not all to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert a man, but to ſtrengthen him; nay after thy beginning the work is behind; not all to <hi>Paul</hi> for planting, but ſome to <hi>Apollos</hi> for watering.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If this man die before the work of grace be finiſhed, even dye before thee; take heed then of a ſenſible decay, or you muſt acknowledge a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall dotage.</p>
            <p n="3">3. From <hi>weakneſſe of judgement,</hi> that looks at the floſcular phraſes; and flouriſhing deckings of their high expreſſions; as if it was a more high and myſterious Divinity then uſually they heare. <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex turba eo pro doctoribus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Marlor <hi>in</hi> Cor.</note> 
               <hi>illos conſuevit ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere; quo minus quae dicunt intelligit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know therefore, 1. How to ſtrip ſuch a <hi>holy day Sermon</hi> of its fine cloathes, and then compare it to plain and old Divinity, and that by the plain and evident truths of God.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:118256:38"/>
            <p n="2">2. Examine ſeriouſly which <hi>comes the neareſt,</hi> and quickeſt to the <hi>heart;</hi> which ſticks moſt in the braine without further deſcent, and faſtening on the conſcience.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Be ſoundly grounded upon the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of Religion, and have them confirmed to thy mind and judgement on Scripture proof, and withall bring in thy own former experience in the wayes of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note n="*" place="margin">Quid vero aſtutius, quidve ſubtilius, quam ut Chriſti ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventu proſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, &amp; inventus inimi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us (poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam lux genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus venit, &amp;c) videns illa ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la derelicta, &amp; per nimium cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentium populu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſedes ſuas, ac Templa dejecta, excogitaverit novam fraude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ut ſub ipſo Chriſtiani no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis titulo fallat ineuntes; haereſes invenit, &amp; ſeiſmata, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſubverteret fidem, veritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corrumperet, ſcinderet unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem; quos deti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere non poteſt in viae veteris cacitate, circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribit, &amp; deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit in novi iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris errore: ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit de ipſa Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia homines, &amp; dum ſibi ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propinquâſſe ja<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lumini, atque e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſiſſe ſaeculi noctem viden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, alias neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes tenebras infundit, &amp;c. <hi>Cypr.</hi> de unit. Eccleſ. <hi>p. 231.</hi>
               </note> From <hi>want of experience, and over Satans wiles:</hi> if he cannot deſtroy, he would diſtract a people: if he cannot keepe them from going to heaven, he would have them at a loſſe, and puzzle them in the way, and fill them full of doubts, croſſe-wayes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in all his propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals to them of new wayes, he will put them under the name of Chriſt, and with the ſame Authority, face, and language as the true way; being an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of light, and his miniſters miniſters of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: and many ſimple ſouls with good intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and aims at higher Spirituall atchievements, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide from the true, and old way of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Therfore, 1. <hi>Beg wiſdome</hi> of the Father: be wiſe as ſerpents to prevent that old ſerpent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Truſt not thy own judgement:</hi> be frequent in the counſells of the righteous.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Unſetledneſſe of ſpirit is a cauſe of Diviſion: not onely a particular doubting of this or that truth, upon ſuch and ſuch grounds of a miſtaken truth, but a generall unſettled frame of mind, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to nothing, no, not to errour it ſelf: as many likewiſe poſſeſſe themſelves with an opinion
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:118256:38"/>of unſetledneſſe; that is, to hang in the expectation of new light in ſubſtance, not a further light in the ſame thing; and maintain that they ſhould not be firm to any thing, not knowing when they have fully obtained a truth, or whether that which now they take for a truth, will hereafter prove an errour, and ſo muſt needs ſtand ready to entertain any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mutation; and to cure this,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Mind the ſtate of thy ſoul, whether thou doſt particularly <hi>increaſe in grace, or no:</hi> ſure if thou findeſt a fruitfulneſſe in reall grace,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.17.18</note> and a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious thriving come upon thy ſoul, thou wilt not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide wavering.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Humbly implore of God (being ſenſible of thine own,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.12.</note> or others lapſings) the ſettlement of his ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Forſake not the Aſſemblies of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.24, 25.</note> whether private, or publick; they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover a tottering mind.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Neglect not any practicall duty, and where thou performeſt it, do it in relation to the promiſe annexed to it; for there is no duty left without the aſſiſtance of a ſpirituall promiſe. If thou beeſt looſe in one way, thou wilt be looſe in many; and if thou beeſt uncertaine with God in any, God may give thee over to a generall looſeneſſe in all; oh therefore, tolerate thy ſelf not in the leaſt evill.</p>
            <p n="6">6. A laſt occaſion and ground of diviſion is a <hi>ſuperlative liberty</hi> due unto <hi>Prerogative ſaints,</hi> under which all heteroclitall judgements lies couched: this hath been ſo much ſearchad into by others, that I need to ſay nothing in reproof, onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:118256:39"/>to every true conſcientious profeſſor theſe conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That none can divide from any Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon hopes of obtaining more purity, light, and Chriſtian liberty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unleſſe he be <hi>infallibly aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> that he falls into a <hi>way more Scripturall,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing to the plain ſpeaking Texts of Scripture: he muſt elſe moſt precipitantly and ignorantly run from them (if the way be not groundedly cleared to him before) or make his liberty of Conſcience a meer pretence for his diviſion, which is either to vex the Church, or pleaſe his luſts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That our Chriſtian <hi>liberty</hi> lies not <hi>looſe,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther under the <hi>definitive determination</hi> of any <hi>man;</hi> but our Chriſtian liberty either lies explained in Chriſts laws in things neceſſary, or may paralel to ſome of his Laws in things indifferent; and theſe Laws are to be eaſily known of all, whereby the happy peace and unity of the Church is much ſetled: Our liberty is a <hi>necesſitous,</hi> not an <hi>arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> liberty; <hi>fixed,</hi> not <hi>unbounded; ordered,</hi> not <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed; reall,</hi> not <hi>imaginary; explained,</hi> not <hi>myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; holy,</hi> not <hi>licencious,</hi> but <hi>wholly ſerving the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That there is no Chriſtian liberty, that <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys naturall affection, civill bonds and intereſts;</hi> that gives way to any ungratefull and unfaithfull treachery in civill matters; but rather confirmes and rightly orders the contrary; much leſſe is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the order, decency, peace and unity of a Church.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the uſe of all <hi>Chriſtian liberty</hi> in things
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:118256:39"/>indifferent is allowed for the <hi>preſervation of our Chriſtian brother,</hi> with whom we are commanded to bear as a weaker brother, not to offend a little one, to lay no ſtumbling blocks before him; which weaker brother you judge to be the Church that you doe forſake, and from whom you divide: that Church dwelling as it were in a lower region, and ſitting in a more unknowing Claſſis then you do; and therefore by the Goſpel rule you ought to have a care that you offend them not (and of them there be many thouſands) in the uſe of your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That all liberty ought to <hi>ſerve unto the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt;</hi> elſe the priviledges of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome would deſtroy the being of it: and ſo by neceſſary conſequence all liberty muſt ſerve to uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Unity being abſolutely neceſſary to the well-being of his Church.</p>
            <p>And that thou maiſt walk like a Chriſtian in the uſe of thy liberty, take theſe Directions. Have not an <hi>overweening conceit</hi> of thy own judgement, worth, and excellency; this will cauſe thee elſe to deſpiſe others, to put thy ſelf before others, and in all actions and diſputes to ſhew more ingenuity, then conſcience. Such a minde is an enemy to the Spirit, ſtands open to temptation, eſpecially to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions, and hath man more then God before his eyes. Be <hi>ſober minded,</hi> and of a <hi>ſober carriage,</hi> for he that hath an intoxicated fancy, and an inebria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted brain, knows not himſelf, nor where he is, he is ſick of wholſome truths, and reels too and fro in his minde from this opinion to that, but adheres to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:118256:40"/>none. Bee you then babes, not in knowledge, but in actions; bee yee little ones as in the eyes of the world, ſo in your own; ſuch will be ſpirituall chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, children aſſociating and uniting together; ſuch ſeldom fall from the truth, and divide from the Church. In a word, let him that names the Lord Jeſus Chriſt depart from iniquity, ſeparate betwixt himſelf and ſin; for its unmortified luſts in us that cauſeth us to divide; let us be contentious againſt ſin within us, ſin without us, ſtriving againſt the corruptions of nature, temptations of Satan, the oppoſitions and allurements of the world: On theſe if a man ſpend his zeal, the ſtrength of ſtrife, the activity of diviſion, he ſhall find much bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly concord and unity in the wayes of Chriſts Kingdom, nor leiſure to diſpute unneceſſaries, nor will to divide for them.</p>
            <p>I am now tedious to my ſelf, much more to you; let me but ſet on theſe inſtructions and directions by a motive or two and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>à</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>à In conjugatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> Piel <hi>ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat dividere.</hi> Therefore the Greeks called them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Leigh</hi> and <hi>Weems.</hi>
               </note>If I could perſwade you that you were guilty of envy, ſtrife, and diviſion, I ſhould perſwade you to leave it, eſpecially thoſe actions wherein they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. I know you ſee it in your ſelves; oh leave this Pharaſaical, this meerly <hi>Pharaſaical way;</hi> the Church of the Jews in their decaying age fell into ſeveral Sects; the Sadduce, the Phariſee, the <hi>watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and the <hi>ſtrict-living</hi> Phariſee, the <hi>Eſſaeni;</hi> and ſo the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in their backſliding age, fell into their <hi>Fryers,</hi> and them of ſeverall ſorts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Oh let this ſcandall paſſe from us, and let us not be in a dying age when we ſhould be reviving; let
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:118256:40"/>us all ſtudy now how to make peace; make it your buſineſs every one of you in your places and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Maſters, Magiſtrates, Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to put on this ſmooth skin, this meek heart, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure peace and unity in the Church of Chriſt; and for this end conſider,</p>
            <p>How the Church of God ſtands towards
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Her ſelf.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Chriſt her Head.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Her Enemies.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the 70 evermore <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregare,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatio,</hi> and ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>Firſt, concerning the Church as ſhe is <hi>in her ſelf:</hi> not only many <hi>precious promiſes</hi> of peace and unity are made unto her, but the Goſpel (the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of promiſes) holds out the ſame by way of direction; love as a ſtream runs thorow the whole channel of Scriptures; its the great cry of all the Prophets and Apoſtles; if it had been an Obſervation ſcattered in one or two places, that had been ſufficient; but its that ſilver ſtring that is drawn thorow all the Epiſtles, and tyed on a moſt compleat knot in St. <hi>Johns</hi> Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>And as theſe <hi>commands</hi> are ſent to the Church and all that is of her, ſo mark under what <hi>Parables</hi> ſhe is ſhadowed forth in Scripture; to name but a few: Shee is frequently compared to a <hi>vineyard,</hi> and that muſt not lie common, but be let forth to husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to be fenced, the trees pruned and watched, the ſtones caſt out, the bryars plucked up and burnt, the Foxes taken; I cannot ſtand to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon all theſe paſſages. Shee is again ſet forth to St. <hi>Peter</hi> under <hi>a ſheet;</hi> this ſheet hath four corners, which are the four parts of the world, out of which the Church was to be called: in theſe are
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:118256:41"/>all creatures, and all theſe are common and mixed together in one ſheet; but as corn of ſeveral grains thrown into a ſheet will ſoon be mingled, ſo all people, nations, and languages without ſeparation, or diſtinction, being called, are to hold communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Shee is frequently compared to a <hi>body,</hi> as in this Epiſtle, not as in reference to Chriſt their Head (as in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.) but in reference one to another, as members. 1. All the members are firmly knit by ſinews. 2. What gifts that any have, the reſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of. 3. There is need of the weakeſt. And here I muſt inſert a Storie much uſed: There were oft grievous broiles betwixt the Commons and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of <hi>Rome:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Livius Decad</hi> 1. l. 7. Mr. <hi>Par.</hi> in Rom. 12.4.</note> once among the reſt, when the people had banded themſelves, and the Common-wealth in great danger, the Senate ſent unto the people one <hi>Menenius Agrippa,</hi> a famous Orator, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them; He tells them this Parable, On a time ſaith he, the members of the body objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtomack, that it devoured all, and idlely and ſluggiſhly lay in the midſt of the body, while the reſt of the members laboured full ſore; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the foot refuſed to ſtir and carry the ſtomack, the hand refuſed to put meat into the mouth, the mouth to receive it, the teeth to chew it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what followed? the ſtomack being empty, the eie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be dim, the hand weak, the feet feeble, all the members began to faint, and the whole body to wither; ſo that at laſt they were compelled to be friends with the ſtomack, and they learned, that the ſtomack is the moſt profitable to all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body; and by this parable he quieted
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:118256:41"/>the people, and brought them to concord with the Senate, and ſo ought it to be in the Church.</p>
            <p>Again let us look upon the Epithites given to her; <hi>Friends,</hi> not only to Chriſt, but to one another; <hi>Brethren,</hi> begat of the ſame word, bound together <hi>per eadem ſacramenta unitatis;</hi> and having ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Egyptian that would have enſlaved you, will you kill one another? not only heirs but co-heirs of one Kingdome, whereof we hear of no diviſion: Nay, to make up all, Shee is called <hi>one;</hi> not onely one by way of diſtinction,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ritas Diſtinguens <hi>&amp;</hi> Conjungens.</note> becauſe the Concubines that pretend ſome right to Chriſt are many, the Papiſt, the Jacobite, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and thoſe that quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominate Chriſt are many, the <hi>Jew, Turk, Perſian &amp;c.</hi> and ſhe is but one, from, and out of all theſe; but one, perfectly one in her ſelf, having one God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe laid together they conſpire nothing but unity; and are they that are of the Church, nay the Church, yet divided? what the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in the Primitive dayes made you ſeem to be by putting on you Bears skins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you really act on one another to your power, by putting on you their hearts and affections. You are Heirs of heaven, but do you expect to ſtand before Chriſt as <hi>Paul</hi>'s or <hi>Apollo's</hi> his diſciples? Will you appear as of this or that ſect or Church? no, no, I am afraid ere then many of your works muſt be burnt, and that by fire, and its well if ſome of you eſcape it; for your works are very rotten and counterfeit: Oh therefore you that profeſſe the true Church, agree of one way, before you appear before the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:118256:42"/>Head of this Church, for I would ſay to ſuch, as the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.7. <hi>Do ye look on things after the outward appearance? if any man truſt to himſelf, that he is Chriſts, let him of himſelf think this again, that as he is Chriſts, even ſo we are Chriſts.</hi> And ſure, if we belong to one Chriſt, why ſhould we be of two Churches? hath he two? Nay, conclude this, from the nature and conſtitution of the Church; For the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Be yee followers of me, even as I alſo am of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us look upon the Church in reference un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Shee is a <hi>Queen</hi> having a garment of divers colours of needle-work, yet all theſe colours, theſe gifts ſo excellently are placed, that they make up that one garment, and her very beautifull in the Kings eyes. Called <hi>a flock,</hi> waſhed, and even ſhorn; not ſcattered, but in one ſheepfold; and all theſe bringing forth twins: The <hi>Houſe of God:</hi> Doth the God of peace dwell in the midſt of you?</p>
            <p>There is <hi>one head, and one body;</hi> one <hi>Spouſe,</hi> and one <hi>Husband;</hi> one <hi>Shepherd,</hi> and one <hi>Flock;</hi> one <hi>Lord,</hi> and one <hi>way:</hi> Eph. 4.1. <hi>I therefore the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner of the Lord, beſeech you that ye walk worthy of the vocation wherewith ye are called.</hi> Mark what he exhorts us unto, <hi>viz.</hi> a walking anſwerable to our calling. And what more anſwers Truth then U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as the natural daughter of the mother? and that is ſhewed, ver. 2, 3, 4— <hi>With all lowlineſs and meekneſs, with long-ſuffering, forbearing one another in love: Endeavouring to keep the unity of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the bond of peace. There is one body,</hi> &amp;c. and he ſhews the means of preſerving this, by uſing our
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:118256:42"/>gifts to this end, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>But unto every one of us is given grace, according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt.</hi> Though all one in ſubſtance, yet different in gifts; yet this difference not to make difference, but to maintain joyntly the unity of the whole, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. And then he applyes this doctrine of Unity by way of dehortation, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. and exhortation and direction, <hi>ver.</hi> 15, 16. Nay, more cannot be ſaid then by the Apoſtle, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.11. —<hi>He that ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifieth, and they who are ſanctified, are all of one: for which cauſe he is not aſhamed to call them bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> And ſure, that vertue whereby we are made one with Chriſt, ſhould make us all as one. God the Father ſo preſerved our Saviour, that his coat was undivided, and not a bone broken: and ſuch ſhould be his myſtical <hi>coat,</hi> the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of his Church; and his myſtical <hi>body,</hi> his <hi>members</hi> in the truth of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> Thoſe then that will keep cloſe to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> need to keep cloſe to his <hi>Church:</hi> He is the fountain; ſtop the fountain, where are the ſtreams? He is the root, that gives ſap onely to the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches uncut off. Surely (Beloved) we ſtop the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain head, we cut our ſelves from Chriſt, if wee leave the body of Chriſt; we indeed loſe our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to Chriſt wholly. And that you may ſee whether it be not ſo, that you loſe Chriſt in loſing his ſpouſe, his body, ſearch and deal with your ſelves impartially, and know of your ſelves ſince your diviſions,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether ſoftnes of heart, and tenderneſſe of conſcience be not leſſened?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether duties of holy practiſe be not neglected?</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:118256:43"/>
            <p n="3">3. Whether, when thou haſt thoughts to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne, pride, in much ſtrength and power appears in thee?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether the very reall warmth of true af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to godly Miniſters, brethren, and naturall friends (if not in thy diviſion) be not decayed?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether much confuſion be not in thy thoughts?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether ſound knowledge, ſaving light that brings peace, and joy on ſure grounds, be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in thee?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether yet thy mind flotes not? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thou makeſt a period in thy preſent diviſion, and there reſts thy mind: Sure by theſe, and the like queries thou mayeſt put to thy ſoul, thou ſhalt find in truth, that thy diviſion from the Church of Chriſt, was a diviſion from Chriſt, and ſince then he hath with-held the moſt ſweet, effectual, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving operations of the ſpirit from thee. Thus if we conſider the Church in it ſelf, &amp; would preſerve it in its eſſence, beauty, and glory; if we look upon her in reference to Chriſt how nearly joyned, we muſt (if we deſire to belong unto Chriſt,) keep cloſe to her; unleſſe thou expecteſt ſalvation out of Chriſt, or Chriſt out of the Church.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we muſt now conſider her as ſhe ſtands in relation to them that are not of her, even to her enemies: And this with the reſt might lay a great ingagement to ſeek her peace, and unity.</p>
            <p>If we conſider her deſiring,
<list>
                  <item>To have them ſaved.</item>
                  <item>To be ſaved from them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, As ſhe deſires to <hi>ſave them,</hi> or to have
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:118256:43"/>
               <hi>them ſav'd.</hi> They cannot be ſav'd out of the Church the dividers themſelves confeſſing: and we muſt or ought to endevour their ſalvation; at leaſt they are to have the tenders of ſalvation, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Who will have all men to be ſaved, and to come unto the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth.</hi> Nay, to have our utmoſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Brethren, my hearts deſire and prayer to God for Iſrael is, that they might be ſaved.</hi> They are your brethren by nature, and queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe many of them in grace too: What have you to wo for you, to invite them in unto you? Peace, a place of unity and reſt, every one deſires; What may they finde with you, that are the Church of God? If not with you, then where? Better it is, will they ſay, to keep a way I have received from my forefathers, and of which I have ſome proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble grounds, then to undertake a new way, where I ſhall find no certainty, loſe that little Religion I have, and find none other unleſſe it be in diſputes, doubts, changes, ſtrifes, diviſions, objections, &amp;c. As once the diſtraction of the Church of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> gave occaſion to a Prince thereof thus to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to thoſe that perſwaded him to turn <hi>Lutheran;</hi> If I aſſociate with you, then I am cenſured of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; if I aſſociate with others,<note place="margin">Si me adjungo vobis, tune con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnor ab aliis; ſi me aliis ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jungo, à vobis condemnor; quid fugiam, vidco; ſed quid ſequar, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habco. <hi>Raul. 2. l. c. 5. Sect. 2. p. 249.</hi>
               </note> then I am cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of you; What to decline I ſee, but what to follow I find not.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then he will enquire for the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of ſalvation; Is the name of God one on whom they call? is the Creed one, and onely one? Its ſaid, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.2. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſſe in the laſt dayes, that the mountain of the Lords houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:118256:44"/>the top of the mountains, and ſhall be exalted above the hills.</hi> Can it be ſaid ſo of us?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Then for <hi>diſcipline:</hi> hee would enjoy the truth with order;<note n="*" place="margin">Chriſtiani propter illas diſſentiones &amp; ſectas in thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris à Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus infidelibus derideri ſoliti fuerant: ſicut etiam nunc in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Turcas, &amp; Judaeos, eandem ob cauſam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur omnes. <hi>Zanch. c. 8 p. 538.</hi>
               </note> Is there no confuſion, diſturbance, rents? Is there no envyings, ſtrifes? &amp;c. Where is your beauty, your amiableneſſe but in this? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.1. <hi>Behold how good, and how pleaſant it is, for brethren to dwel together in unity.</hi> Chriſt Saith, <hi>Let your light ſhine before all men.</hi> and <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Let your moderation be known unto all men.</hi> Your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion not onely drawes ſome weak ſouls after you, but keeps back many a ſoul from coming into the Church, loſes and deſtroyes ſoules, juſtly open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the mouths of wicked ones againſt you, whoſe holy and peaceable converſation ſhould ſtop them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You deſire <hi>to ſave your ſelves;</hi> then keep your walls in repair; that as <hi>Sanballat</hi> and <hi>Tobiah</hi> ſaid of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> their walls were ſo bad, a fox might run over them; and ſo truly of our Church; theſe, indeed, invite the thief to enter when the walls are down: and as you keep them in repair, ſo your ſelves in unitie; for your diviſion weakens your ſelves: for envy through diviſions may ariſe ſo high, that one partie may ſit down to ſee the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſtroyed, though a worſe come in their room: whereas their unitie might preſerve them both. Experience, reaſon, and truth maintains this, to what ſad ruines it hath brought famous Cities, Churches and Common-wealths: for envie, ſtrife and diviſion never ceaſe, till they be buried in ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines, unleſſe God reconcile their hearts: As two poſts leaning upon one another, either ſtand by the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:118256:44"/>ſtrength, or fall by the weakneſs one of another. Nature, Reaſon, Hiſtorie, Experience and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture fruitfully prove theſe things.</p>
            <p>Conſidering all theſe, if any thing be dear to you, to you that ſhould have the bowels of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; if the <hi>ſpouſe</hi> of Chriſt, if your <hi>own unity</hi> with Chriſt the Head, if the <hi>ſalvation</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> and your own <hi>temporall preſervation</hi> be valued of you, lay aſide theſe envyings, ſtrifes, and diviſions; hold that one Faith in Unity, be knit together (as you would be to Chriſt) as one man; and where you ſee occaſions of diviſion, refuſalls of union, drive and force upon men terms of unity; this is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to perſecute one another with peace; And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for Chriſts ſake, for his <hi>Churches ſake,</hi> for the <hi>ſtrangers ſake,</hi> for your <hi>own ſake,</hi> I beſeech you to lay to heart what hath been ſaid; help to make up breaches you have made, and to honour the truth in your ſecond return, and re-union to the Church of Chriſt. And ſo with the Apoſtles exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to theſe <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. we conclude, <hi>Now I beſeech you, brethren, by the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that yee all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no diviſions among you: but that ye be perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde, and in the ſame judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
